<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>maths on Josia's Blog</title><link>https://jscheytt.github.io/tags/maths/</link><description>Recent content in maths on Josia's Blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Oct 2021 08:32:23 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jscheytt.github.io/tags/maths/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Guessing UUIDs would actually take very long</title><link>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/guessing-uuids-would-actually-take-very-long/</link><pubDate>Wed, 06 Oct 2021 08:32:23 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/guessing-uuids-would-actually-take-very-long/</guid><description>&lt;p>UUIDs are 128-bit numbers.
That means they have $2^{128}$ possible values which is roughly $3 \cdot 10^{38}$ (or in scientific notation, 3e38).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Does this range make it safe for cryptographic purposes?
Most people on the internet say an emphatic &amp;ldquo;No!&amp;rdquo;, so I am just keeping this here as a ðŸš¨ disclaimer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But is it at least &lt;strong>collision-safe&lt;/strong>?
I think definitely yes.
And is it also &lt;strong>guess-safe&lt;/strong>?
Let&amp;rsquo;s explore that question with a bit of maths:&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="example-scenario">Example Scenario&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Let&amp;rsquo;s say you have an API and you know the records are referenced by their UUID.
And let&amp;rsquo;s say you wanted to guess any valid record (because &lt;a class="link" href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/3652944/how-securely-unguessable-are-guids" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>ðŸ’° money&lt;/a>).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What is a realistic scenario, i.e. a reasonably expectable time it would take you to find a valid record?
Let&amp;rsquo;s just naively assume you find a valid UUID after randomly iterating over half of all possible UUIDs.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="how-long-would-that-take-you">How long would that take you?&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Imagine you had started firing requests at your hypothetical API &lt;strong>at the beginning of the observable universe&lt;/strong>, i.e. about 1.3772e10 years (or 4.3437e17 seconds) ago.
And you send requests at a rate of &lt;strong>1 trillion (1e12) requests per second&lt;/strong> (and, of course, your target API responds at the same rate ðŸ˜‰).
(You would have to be &lt;em>very&lt;/em> physically close to the API server - at a trillionth of a second, light and therefore information travels only a measly 0.3 millimeters &amp;hellip;)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>How many UUIDs would you have covered?
You would have processed barely &lt;strong>1 billionth of all possible UUIDs&lt;/strong> (to be precise: 1e12 * 4,3437e17 / 2^128 â‰ˆ 1.2765e-9).
That is not even remotely close to half of all UUIDs.
To cover half of all possible UUIDs you would have to continue for another &amp;hellip; how many years?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$
\frac{(1.2765 \cdot 10^{9} - 1) \cdot 4.3437 \cdot 10^{17} \ seconds}{2} = 2.7725 \cdot 10^{26} \ seconds = 8.786 \cdot 10^{18} \ years
$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>And these roughly 10 quintillion years are roughly &lt;strong>1 billion times the age of the universe&lt;/strong>.
So you would very probably never live to see the matching of the UUID.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But, just hypothetically assuming you have started your client&amp;rsquo;s requests at the dawn of time and can continue to run it on this Earth unattended for as long as this planet exists:
Would you still &lt;strong>physically have enough time&lt;/strong> to execute your requests (for half of all UUIDs)?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We are going into &lt;a class="link" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Timeline_of_the_far_future" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>lots of speculation&lt;/a> now, but:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>In latest 2e9 years, all life will have vanished from Earth, the oceans have evaporated, the surface temperature will reach around 150 Â° C.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>You better build your client and API servers very temperature robust ðŸœ &amp;hellip;&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>In 1e14 years, all stars will have exhausted their fuel.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Assuming the Earth has not been completely engulfed by the Sun during its red giant phase,
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>and assuming the Earth was not already ejected from its orbit into outer space (not another galaxy),&lt;/li>
&lt;li>then the Earth would surely collide with the then black dwarf Sun in 10e20 years.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>So yes, with a bit of preparation (temperature hardening, robust solar panels, radiation shielding) your client server would probably finish &lt;em>just in time&lt;/em> before the Earth itself becomes mere history ðŸ˜‰.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>