<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Today I Learned That ... on Josia's Blog</title><link>https://jscheytt.github.io/categories/today-i-learned/</link><description>Recent content in Today I Learned That ... on Josia's Blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 08:34:20 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jscheytt.github.io/categories/today-i-learned/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>You can Gitopsify your Ansible</title><link>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/you-can-gitopsify-your-ansible/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 08:34:20 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/you-can-gitopsify-your-ansible/</guid><description>I have a dotfiles repository for setting up my MacOS machine easily and reproducibly. For this I am mostly using Ansible, just slightly wrapping it with Make and seasoning it with a pinch of Shell.
The core piece of this repository is a Brewfile and a collection of Shell aliases and functions. I don&amp;rsquo;t regularly run the Ansible playbook itself because I created it for initially setting up a machine. The only thing I run very frequently is the upgrade command which includes persisting new Brew formulae to the Brewfile.</description></item><item><title>kubectl can explain all resource types in detail</title><link>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/kubectl-can-explain-all-resource-types-in-detail/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 14:53:18 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/kubectl-can-explain-all-resource-types-in-detail/</guid><description>$ kubectl explain statefulset KIND: StatefulSet VERSION: apps/v1 DESCRIPTION: StatefulSet represents a set of pods with consistent identities. Identities are defined as: - Network: A single stable DNS and hostname. - Storage: As many VolumeClaims as requested. The StatefulSet guarantees that a given network identity will always map to the same storage identity. FIELDS: apiVersion &amp;lt;string&amp;gt; APIVersion defines the versioned schema of this representation of an object. Servers should convert recognized schemas to the latest internal value, and may reject unrecognized values.</description></item><item><title>Trying to simplify k8s labels can be dangerous for your routing</title><link>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/trying-to-simplify-k8s-labels-can-be-dangerous-for-your-routing/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Dec 2021 10:43:01 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/trying-to-simplify-k8s-labels-can-be-dangerous-for-your-routing/</guid><description>Today I was refactoring a bigger configuration setup that is built with kustomize. I see kustomize as a light-weight way of packaging multiple Kubernetes manifests, together with a little bit of logic.
The base kustomization of the application config repo I was refactoring looked something like this:
apiVersion:kustomize.config.k8s.io/v1beta1kind:Kustomizationresources:- manifests/cronjob-backup.yaml- manifests/deployment.yaml- manifests/ingress.yaml- manifests/pod-disruption-budget.yaml- manifests/service.yamlcommonAnnotations:source:javatenant:acmeconfigMapGenerator:- name:acme-app-configfiles:- configs/10-local.properties- configs/30-local.properties- configs/40-local.propertiesI have an almost pathologic tendency to simplify and DRY everything up that I find, especially in configuration code.</description></item><item><title>Kubernetes is still willing to show you Dangling Resources in your Terminating Namespace</title><link>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/kubernetes-is-still-willing-to-show-you-dangling-resources-in-your-terminating-namespace/</link><pubDate>Fri, 29 Oct 2021 12:11:47 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/kubernetes-is-still-willing-to-show-you-dangling-resources-in-your-terminating-namespace/</guid><description>kubectl api-resources --verbs=list --namespaced -o name \ | xargs -n 1 kubectl get --show-kind --ignore-not-found -n &amp;#34;$NAMESPACE&amp;#34; Props to RedHat.</description></item><item><title>HTML limits you to a signed 32-bit int in ordered lists</title><link>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/html-limits-you-to-a-signed-32-bit-int-in-ordered-lists/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Sep 2021 08:55:22 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/html-limits-you-to-a-signed-32-bit-int-in-ordered-lists/</guid><description>HTML allows you to specify a starting number from which an ordered list (&amp;lt;ol&amp;gt;) should start. I thought &amp;ldquo;Is there an upper bound?&amp;rdquo;.
Turns out: Yes, there is. It&amp;rsquo;s 2147483647 (i.e. 231-1 ). Looks like a signed 32-bit integer to me.
&amp;lt;ol start=2147483645&amp;gt; &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;I am still in order&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt; &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;As am I&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt; &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;Me too&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt; &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;💥 Limit reached&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt; &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;💥 Limit reached&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt; &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;💥 Limit reached&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/ol&amp;gt; The above snippet will render as the following:</description></item><item><title>You can create TOTP tokens via CLI without a smartphone</title><link>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/you-can-create-totp-tokens-via-cli-without-a-smartphone/</link><pubDate>Fri, 27 Aug 2021 08:20:41 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/you-can-create-totp-tokens-via-cli-without-a-smartphone/</guid><description>All you need is the secret of your TOTP.
The QR code is just a representation of a oath:// URL That URL contains the secret as a query parameter.
# Install oathtool brew install oathtool # Use your secret, e.g. as a base32-encoded string oathtool --totp --base32 &amp;#34;MFRGCZDTMVRXEZLUBI======&amp;#34;</description></item><item><title>Docker does not really help you a lot trying to get permissions right</title><link>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/docker-does-not-really-help-you-a-lot-trying-to-get-permissions-right/</link><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jul 2021 14:42:07 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/docker-does-not-really-help-you-a-lot-trying-to-get-permissions-right/</guid><description>I really love Docker, and I also come to like security more and more. One advice I have been hearing a lot (e.g. in this Container Security Cheat Sheet from Snyk) is that you should not run your container as a root user.
&amp;ldquo;Easy thing,&amp;rdquo; I thought to myself, &amp;ldquo;I am just going to put something like USER {app}&amp;rdquo; at the top of my Dockerfile.&amp;quot; Well, think again, because:
FROMnode:ltsUSERnode# I would have thought that after this point, every action will happen in the name of this user# and also that every created directory and file will belong to this user .</description></item><item><title>You can :wq in vim with :x</title><link>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/you-can-wq-in-vim-with-x/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/you-can-wq-in-vim-with-x/</guid><description>I have developed quite some muscle memory in terminating vim via :wqa. Now I can save one more character by retraining myself to use :xa! 😄
I also like how :x sort of symbolizes the close button ❌ of many window managers and their default behavior of saving when you close a file.
For more documentation open vim and type :h :x.
Wait, now that you mention it &amp;hellip; Well, turns out the documentation mentions an even easier way: Just press ZZ (without the colon) 😴</description></item></channel></rss>