<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>jesus on Josia's Blog</title><link>https://jscheytt.github.io/tags/jesus/</link><description>Recent content in jesus on Josia's Blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Josia Scheytt</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 21 Oct 2023 13:28:49 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jscheytt.github.io/tags/jesus/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Eine neue Psalmen-Liturgie</title><link>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/eine-neue-psalmen-liturgie/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Oct 2023 13:28:49 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/eine-neue-psalmen-liturgie/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>In diesem Post stelle ich eine 2-Wochen-Liturgie basierend auf den Psalmen vor.
Dieses Stundengebet verwende ich selbst privat; es ist aber durchaus für den Gebrauch in Gemeinschaften gedacht, die das Leben im Reich Gottes einüben wollen.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Wenn du die Hintergründe überspringen willst, spule direkt vor zur &lt;a class="link" href="#die-liturgie" >eigentlichen Liturgie&lt;/a>.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Die Psalmen sind ein besonderer Schatz in der Bibel, sind sie doch gleichzeitig das Wort Gottes und Worte von Menschen.
Mithilfe dieser verschriftlichen Gespräche mit Gott, die Menschen lange vor uns geführt und festgehalten haben, haben wir eine extrem praktische Hilfe, um unser ganzes Innenleben vor Gott auszubreiten und dadurch Beziehung zu Ihm zu führen.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Vor einigen Jahren habe ich angefangen, diesen Schatz bewusst zu entdecken und in meinen eigenen Gebetszeiten zu verwenden.
Da ich sowieso meine Beziehung zu Gott viel dadurch führe, dass ich Sein Wort verwende (vor allem durch lautes Lesen und Auswendiglernen), fiel mir das nicht sonderlich schwer.
Ich begann mit einer fortlaufenden Lesung (&amp;ldquo;Lectio continua&amp;rdquo;), bei der ich mit Psalm 1 begann, am nächsten Tag Psalm 2 las, am nächsten Tag Psalm 3 und so weiter, bis ich nach Psalm 150 wieder von vorne anfing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So ging es mehrere Jahre, bis ich merkte, dass ich einen Stopp oder eine Veränderung brauchte, um nicht betriebsblind für die Inhalte der Psalmen zu werden.
Ich wusste nicht, wie eine gesunde Alternative zur Lectio continua aussehen könnte, aber ich pausierte mein kontinuierliches Psalmengebet und suchte nun nach neuen Möglichkeiten, mit dem ganzen Psalter in meinem Alltag zu beten.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="stundengebete">Stundengebete&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Durch verschiedene Ansatzpunkte und Gespräche mit Freunden traf ich auf Stundengebete.
Damit sind Gebetsformen gemeint, bei denen man (ähnlich der rituellen Gebetszeiten der Muslime) zu mehreren festgelegten Zeiten am Tag betet, oftmals mit vorformulierten Gebeten.
Das fand ich ansprechend, da ich von meiner Persönlichkeit her sehr strukturiert bin und gleichzeitig immer mehr lernen will, in meinem &lt;em>ganzen&lt;/em> Alltag mit Gott verbunden zu sein.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Leider waren die ersten Gebetsbücher mit vorformulierten Gebeten, auf die ich traf, für meinen Geschmack zu einseitig und zu wenig auf Gott beziehend.
Durch Gottes Gnade landete ich irgendwann beim Mönchstum und fand einen Orden, deren Gebetsbuch zum Haupteil aus den Psalmen besteht.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Dieser Orden sind die &lt;strong>&lt;a class="link" href="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benediktiner" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Benediktiner&lt;/a>&lt;/strong>, einer der weltweit größten Mönchsorden, beheimatet in der katholischen Kirche und benannt nach ihrem Gründer Benedikt von Nursia (6. Jahrhundert).
In der &lt;a class="link" href="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stundengebet#Benediktsregel" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Ordensregel&lt;/a> schreibt der Heilige Benedikt seinen Ordensbrüdern vor, dass sie &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.intratext.com/IXT/DEU0017/_PJ.HTM" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>einmal in der Woche den ganzen Psalter durchbeten sollen&lt;/a> - jede Woche in jedem Jahr.
In dieser Regel sind auch &lt;a class="link" href="http://individual.utoronto.ca/aaronorear/psalmody.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>einige konkrete Aufteilungen&lt;/a> der Psalmen auf Wochentage und Gebetszeiten enthalten, worauf Benedikt allerdings nicht streng beharrt (siehe &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.intratext.com/IXT/DEU0017/_PJ.HTM" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>RB 18,20&lt;/a>).
Ebenso schreibt die Benedikts-Regel &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.intratext.com/IXT/DEU0017/_PH.HTM" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>sieben tägliche Gebetszeiten&lt;/a> vor (wobei die meisten heutigen Klöster nur 4 - 5 Gebetszeiten ausüben, indem sie einige der vorgeschriebenen Zeiten kombinieren).&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="benediktinische-psalmenliturgie">Benediktinische Psalmenliturgie&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Eines der bekannteren Benediktinerklöster in Deutschland steht in Münsterschwarzach.
Bekannt ist es unter anderem durch den schriftstellerisch sehr aktiven und dort ansässigen Benediktinermönch Anselm Grün.
Was ebenfalls von dort stammt, ist das &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.vier-tuerme.de/benediktinisches-antiphonale-komplettpaket-mit-baenden-i-bis-iii" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Benediktinische Antiphonale&lt;/a>&lt;/strong>&amp;rdquo;, ein mehrbändiges Gebetsbuch mit fast 2.000 Seiten.
Dieses Gebetsbuch enthält eine Liturgie, bei der alle Psalmen in einer sorgfältig aufeinander abgestimmten Reihenfolge zusammengestellt und mit gottesdienstlichen Elementen aus der katholischen Tradition verwoben sind.
Die liturgische Zusammenstellung aus diesem Kloster wird mittlerweile in vielen deutschsprachigen Benediktinerklöstern verwandt.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Nicht nur die Positionierung der Psalmen ist in diesem Fall besonders (wir betrachten gleich genauer, warum), sondern auch der Text:
Auch wenn die Mönche ihrer Kirche treu sein und die Einheitsübersetzung verwenden wollten, taten sie sich doch sehr schwer damit, weil sie so wenig singbar war.
Deswegen entschlossen sich einige Benediktiner aus verschiedenen Klöstern, gemeinsam eine &lt;strong>komplett eigene Übersetzung der Psalmen aus dem hebräischen Urtext&lt;/strong> zu erstellen.
Diese Neuübersetzung sollte einerseits der poetischen Form der Psalmen Rechnung tragen (durch Klarheit, Kürze und Sprachrhythmus) und sich andererseits auch für ihren gregorianischen Gesang im Kloster eignen.
Diese Übersetzung der Psalmen, deren Redaktion in Münsterschwarzach stattfand, ist mittlerweile auch getrennt von der restlichen Liturgie erhältlich als &amp;ldquo;&lt;em>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bookfinder.com/isbn/9783878682363/?st=sr&amp;amp;ac=qr&amp;amp;mode=basic&amp;amp;author=&amp;amp;title=&amp;amp;isbn=9783878682363&amp;amp;lang=de&amp;amp;destination=de&amp;amp;currency=EUR&amp;amp;binding=*&amp;amp;keywords=&amp;amp;publisher=&amp;amp;min_year=&amp;amp;max_year=&amp;amp;minprice=&amp;amp;maxprice=" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Münsterschwarzacher Psalter&lt;/a>&lt;/em>&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Bei der Zusammenstellung der Psalmen gingen die Mönche (darunter sticht am meisten &lt;a class="link" href="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Notker_F%C3%BCglister" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Notker Füglister&lt;/a> hervor) mit tiefem Verständnis von Literatur und großer Liebe zu Gott und Seinem Wort vor:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Sie ordneten die Psalmen (so weit möglich) bestimmten &lt;strong>Tageszeiten&lt;/strong> zu. Beispiele:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Psalm 5 &amp;ldquo;Am Morgen wirst du mein Rufen hören&amp;rdquo; für morgens&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sie setzten sie auch bewusst an bestimmte &lt;strong>Wochentage&lt;/strong>. Beispiele:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Messianische Psalmen (z. B. Psalm 2) an die Sonntage&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Psalm 22 &amp;ldquo;Mein Gott, mein Gott, warum hast du mich verlassen?&amp;rdquo; an den Freitagmittag (wegen Karfreitag)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ihrer Ansicht nach stehen &lt;strong>alle Psalmen in Beziehung zueinander&lt;/strong> und &amp;ldquo;sind miteinander im Gespräch&amp;rdquo;. Beispiele:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Psalm 100 und 95 stehen fast benachbart in einer Gebetszeit und enthalten beide die Zeile &amp;ldquo;Wir sind das Volk Deiner Weide, die Herde Deiner Hand&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Psalm 58 und 82 stehen benachbart und klagen ungerecht handelnde Mächtige an.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Psalm 29, 1 und 19 stehen zusammen und bestaunen Gottes Reden und Sein Gesetz.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Jeder Psalm wurde &lt;strong>am Stück&lt;/strong> gebetet und nicht in einzelne Versabschnitte zerstückelt
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Einzige Ausnahme ist Psalm 119, den mit Abstand längsten Psalm, der allerdings natürlicherweise aus 22 Strophen besteht.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Weiterhin machten die Mönche an manchen Stellen Vereinfachungen bei der &lt;strong>Zählung und Aufteilung der Psalmen&lt;/strong>:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Drei Psalmen werden ausgelassen&lt;/strong>, weil sie vollständig in anderen Psalmen enthalten sind:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Psalm 53 = Psalm 14&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Psalm 70 = Psalm 40,14-18&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Psalm 108 = Psalm 57,8-12 = Psalm 60,7-14&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Manche Psalmen werden &lt;strong>zusammengefasst&lt;/strong>:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Psalm 9 und 10 sind einer der alphabetischen Psalmen, bei denen jeder Vers (oder jeder x-te Vers) mit dem nächsten Buchstaben des hebräischen Alphabets beginnt, sodass 9 und 10 generell als Einheit betrachtet werden.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Psalm 42 und 43 haben einen identischen Refrain und werden ebenfalls als Einheit betrachtet.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Psalm 119&lt;/strong> als der längste Psalm besteht aus 22 Strophen und wird nicht komplett am Stück gelesen.
Stattdessen werden die einzelnen Strophen an bestimmten Stellen in der Liturgie als sogenanntes &amp;ldquo;Responsorium&amp;rdquo; eingebaut.
(Ich konnte leider nicht genauer herausfinden, wo sie eingebaut wurden und ob es dabei irgendein bewusstes Muster gab.)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="eine-eigene-liturgie-entsteht">Eine eigene Liturgie entsteht&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="antiphonale-brevier-psalter">Antiphonale, Brevier, Psalter&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Dank der Unibibliothek in unserer Nähe konnte ich sowohl den Münsterschwarzacher Psalter als auch eine Kurzfassung des Antiphonale, das &amp;ldquo;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bookfinder.com/isbn/9783736501263/?st=sr&amp;amp;ac=qr&amp;amp;mode=basic&amp;amp;author=&amp;amp;title=&amp;amp;isbn=9783736501263&amp;amp;lang=de&amp;amp;destination=de&amp;amp;currency=EUR&amp;amp;binding=*&amp;amp;keywords=&amp;amp;publisher=&amp;amp;min_year=&amp;amp;max_year=&amp;amp;minprice=&amp;amp;maxprice=" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Benediktinische Brevier&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo; ausleihen.
Das Brevier enthält alle Liturgieteile außer die Vigilien (die Vigil ist die allererste Gebetszeit).
Die Vigilien enthalten allerdings 54 Psalmen; dadurch fehlt im Brevier mehr als ein Drittel aller Psalmen.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Dennoch konnte ich mithilfe des Breviers auch ohne direkten Zugriff auf ein Kloster oder Mönche die Antiphonale-Liturgie in ihrer Vollständigkeit ausprobieren.
Kurz gesagt war es als Nichtkatholik zu viel Neues für mich, auch wenn sie sehr viele wertvolle Elemente enthält wie schriftbasierte Gesänge, Schuldbekenntnisse und Fürbitte.
Spannenderweise sind für hohe Feiertage besondere Zusatztexte oder Abweichungen im Ablauf vorgesehen, was wiederum zeigt, aus welch reichem Schatz an Tradition und Kirchengeschichte die Mönche schöpfen.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Im Münsterschwarzacher Psalter hingegen fand ich dann zum ersten Mal eine Kurzbeschreibung der Psalmenaufteilung des Benediktinischen Antiphonale.
Die Aufteilung ist wie folgt:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>Wochentag&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Vigil Inv.&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Vigil I&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Vigil II&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Laudes&lt;/th>
&lt;th>MH I&lt;/th>
&lt;th>MH II&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Abendhore&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Nachthore&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Sonntag&lt;/td>
&lt;td>81&lt;/td>
&lt;td>110&lt;/td>
&lt;td>45&lt;/td>
&lt;td>93&lt;/td>
&lt;td>118&lt;/td>
&lt;td>136&lt;/td>
&lt;td>113&lt;/td>
&lt;td>4&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>18&lt;/td>
&lt;td>9/10&lt;/td>
&lt;td>3&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>114&lt;/td>
&lt;td>91&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2&lt;/td>
&lt;td>72&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>115&lt;/td>
&lt;td>134&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>147&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>116&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Montag&lt;/td>
&lt;td>29&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1&lt;/td>
&lt;td>94&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100&lt;/td>
&lt;td>25&lt;/td>
&lt;td>120&lt;/td>
&lt;td>33&lt;/td>
&lt;td>34&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>104&lt;/td>
&lt;td>105&lt;/td>
&lt;td>63&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>121&lt;/td>
&lt;td>61&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>71&lt;/td>
&lt;td>112&lt;/td>
&lt;td>101&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>122&lt;/td>
&lt;td>28&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>135&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>48&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Dienstag&lt;/td>
&lt;td>67&lt;/td>
&lt;td>6&lt;/td>
&lt;td>74&lt;/td>
&lt;td>98&lt;/td>
&lt;td>42/43&lt;/td>
&lt;td>123&lt;/td>
&lt;td>75&lt;/td>
&lt;td>139&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>107&lt;/td>
&lt;td>73&lt;/td>
&lt;td>90&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>124&lt;/td>
&lt;td>140&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>7&lt;/td>
&lt;td>77&lt;/td>
&lt;td>65&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>125&lt;/td>
&lt;td>26&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>117&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>145&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Mittwoch&lt;/td>
&lt;td>46&lt;/td>
&lt;td>78&lt;/td>
&lt;td>58&lt;/td>
&lt;td>97&lt;/td>
&lt;td>44&lt;/td>
&lt;td>126&lt;/td>
&lt;td>103&lt;/td>
&lt;td>32&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>132&lt;/td>
&lt;td>19&lt;/td>
&lt;td>36&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>127&lt;/td>
&lt;td>86&lt;/td>
&lt;td>62&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>49&lt;/td>
&lt;td>57&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>128&lt;/td>
&lt;td>85&lt;/td>
&lt;td>133&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>82&lt;/td>
&lt;td>149&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>87&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Donnerstag&lt;/td>
&lt;td>24&lt;/td>
&lt;td>39&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50&lt;/td>
&lt;td>47&lt;/td>
&lt;td>55&lt;/td>
&lt;td>129&lt;/td>
&lt;td>11&lt;/td>
&lt;td>102&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>37&lt;/td>
&lt;td>68&lt;/td>
&lt;td>76&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>130&lt;/td>
&lt;td>23&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>41&lt;/td>
&lt;td>83&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>131&lt;/td>
&lt;td>84&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>148&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Freitag&lt;/td>
&lt;td>8&lt;/td>
&lt;td>88&lt;/td>
&lt;td>60&lt;/td>
&lt;td>96&lt;/td>
&lt;td>22&lt;/td>
&lt;td>11&lt;/td>
&lt;td>144&lt;/td>
&lt;td>31&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>69&lt;/td>
&lt;td>106&lt;/td>
&lt;td>143&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>12&lt;/td>
&lt;td>141&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>38&lt;/td>
&lt;td>79&lt;/td>
&lt;td>64&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>13&lt;/td>
&lt;td>142&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>146&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>27&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Samstag&lt;/td>
&lt;td>95&lt;/td>
&lt;td>59&lt;/td>
&lt;td>137&lt;/td>
&lt;td>99&lt;/td>
&lt;td>35&lt;/td>
&lt;td>52&lt;/td>
&lt;td>66&lt;/td>
&lt;td>15&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>109&lt;/td>
&lt;td>89&lt;/td>
&lt;td>51&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>14&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20&lt;/td>
&lt;td>16&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>56&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80&lt;/td>
&lt;td>92&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>54&lt;/td>
&lt;td>21&lt;/td>
&lt;td>17&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>150&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>138&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>In dieser Zusammenstellung sind die Psalmen verteilt auf fünf Gebetszeiten:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Vigil mit Invitatorium und Teil I (in 1. Wochen) oder Teil II (in 2. Wochen)
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Meist um 05:30&lt;/li>
&lt;li>In einigen Klöstern folgt die Laudes direkt im Anschluss auf die Vigil.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Laudes&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Mittagshore (abgekürzt mit &amp;ldquo;MH&amp;rdquo;) mit Teil I (in 1. Wochen) oder Teil II (in 2. Wochen)
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Meist um 12:00&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Abendhore (auch &amp;ldquo;Vesper&amp;rdquo;)
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Meist um 17:30&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Das Wort &amp;ldquo;Hore&amp;rdquo; bedeutet wörtlich &amp;ldquo;Stunde&amp;rdquo; (wie engl. &amp;ldquo;hour&amp;rdquo;) und steht für eine einzelne Gebetszeit.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Nachthore (auch &amp;ldquo;Komplet&amp;rdquo;)
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Meist um 19:00&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Ursprünglich hatte ich fälschlicherweise angenommen, dass Vigil I/II und Mittagshore I/II immer zusammen gebetet werden.
Erst bei einem kürzlichen Besuch in einem Kloster stellte ich meinen Irrtum fest:
Es werden alternierend Vigil I mit Mittagshore I und in der anschließenden Woche Vigil II mit Mittagshore II gebetet, während die restlichen Elemente gleich bleiben.
Dadurch werden doch nicht alle Psalmen in exakt einer Woche gebetet; es sind durchschnittlich 110 Psalmen pro Woche (also ungefähr 75 %).&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="ziele-und-gestaltungsprinzipien">Ziele und Gestaltungsprinzipien&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Mit dieser obigen Tabelle hatte ich einen extrem wertvollen Startpunkt für eine eigene Liturgie.
Bei der Gestaltung dieser Psalmenliturgie waren mir folgende Dinge besonders wichtig:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Der Psalter soll mit &lt;strong>vertretbarem Zeitaufwand&lt;/strong> nutzbar sein, sowohl für Einzelpersonen als auch für geistliche Gemeinschaften, die täglich gemeinsame Gebetszeiten pflegen wollen.
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Deswegen habe ich ihn auf &lt;strong>zwei Wochen&lt;/strong> verteilt.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Grobe Rechnung dazu:&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Bei 145 Psalmen (siehe die obigen Auslassungen) und 14 Tagen kommt man auf 10 bis 11 Psalmen am Tag.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>In der Audioversion der &amp;ldquo;Hoffnung für alle&amp;rdquo; dauern die Psalmen in Summe ziemlich genau sechs Stunden.
Damit sind wir bei durchschnittlich ca. &lt;em>25 Minuten reiner Lesezeit pro Tag&lt;/em>.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ebenfalls aus Gründen der Machbarkeit habe ich &lt;strong>drei Horen&lt;/strong> gewählt:
Morgen, Mittag, Abend.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Die Mittagshore soll kürzer sein, weil in Gemeinschaften womöglich nicht alle Mitglieder mittags anwesend sein können.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Bei drei Horen und zwei Wochen ergibt sich eine Psalmenanzahl von durchschnittlich &lt;em>3 - 4 Psalmen pro Hore&lt;/em>.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Außerdem sollen die &lt;strong>Horen ungefähr gleich lang&lt;/strong> sein für bessere Planbarkeit und um Zeitdruck zu vermeiden.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Als Ausnahme können die Horen an Samstagen und Sonntagen länger sein, weil wir hier davon ausgehen können, dass wir mehr Zeit zur Verfügung haben.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Biblische Texte&lt;/strong> sollen die Grundlage bilden.
Bei außerbiblische Gebeten haben wir eine zu schwer überschaubare Auswahl.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Die &lt;strong>Anordnung der Psalmen&lt;/strong> zueinander aus dem Antiphonale soll so weit wie möglich &lt;strong>erhalten&lt;/strong> bleiben, um aus dem reichen Erfahrungsschatz der benediktinischen Mönche zu schöpfen.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Als Ergänzung sollen auch &lt;strong>neutestamentliche Texte&lt;/strong> mit einfließen.
Nur Psalmen zu lesen ohne den Bezug zu Christus ist auf Dauer unausgewogen.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Psalm 119&lt;/strong> soll am Ende der Morgen- und Mittagshoren stehen.
Damit können wir zum Start in den Vormittag und dann zum Start in den Nachmittag jeweils bekräftigen, dass wir unter Jesu Herrschaft und im Einklang mit Seinem Willen leben möchten.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Zu Psalm 119 habe ich ein &lt;a class="link" href="https://jscheytt.github.io/p/the-beauty-of-the-law/" >besonderes Verhältnis&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h3 id="erste-schritte">Erste Schritte&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Die Umstrukturierung des Antiphonale begann anfänglich mit Fokus auf der Umverteilung der fünf bestehenden Horen auf die drei neuen Horen:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Die &lt;em>neue Laudes&lt;/em> nimmt die originale Laudes und von den Vigilien das Invitatorium und Teil I.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Die Vigil und die Laudes des Sonntags blieb an ihrem Platz (die Laudes an Sonntag I, die Vigil an Sonntag II).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>An den anderen Tagen wechseln sich Laudes und Vigil Inv+I ab.
(Dieses Abwechseln hat sich insgesamt bewährt, damit vollständig erhaltene Segmente aus dem Antiphonale sich abwechseln können mit stärker umsortierten Horen.)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Die &lt;em>neue Mittagshore&lt;/em> nimmt die originale Mittagshore I und II und den Sonntag, Montag und Dienstag der Vigil II.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Die &lt;em>neue Abendhore&lt;/em> nimmt die originale Abendhore, Nachthore und Mittwoch bis Samstag (die übrigen Tage) der Vigil II.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Jede Hore besteht aus drei Teilen:
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Ein oder mehrere Psalmen als Hauptteil&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Eine Schriftlesung aus dem Neuen Testament&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ein Abschlusspsalm&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Als ich eine erste Version zusammengebaut hatte, testete ich sie umgehend im Alltag.
Über viele Wochen hinweg verfeinerte ich die Zusammenstellung an vielen Stellen:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a class="link" href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/14AuC6JHy1GkDbFyaH_jHxm-OzG-m8ZMW?rtpof=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Dank Excel&lt;/a> konnte ich den Mittelwert und die Standardabweichung der Leselängen der einzelnen Horen bestimmen.
Dadurch konnte ich diese Werte in immer besseres Fahrwasser bringen für eine möglichst einheitliche Länge.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Die Aufteilung der 22 Strophen von Psalm 119 war anfänglich auf allen Morgenden und Mittagen und zusätzlich auf dem Samstagmorgen.
Allerdings waren einige der späteren 119-Strophen inhaltlich besser für den Abend bzw. Morgen geeignet.
Deswegen sortierte ich sie um, sodass der Samstag I jetzt keine 119-Strophen mehr enthält, aber dafür der Samstag II.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Für die NT-Texte nutzte ich die Texte, die bereits im Antiphonale vorkamen und einige NT-Texte, die uns als Hauskreis wichtig sind.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Manche Konstellationen von Psalmen waren sehr bitter und hoffnungslos.
Das darf unsere Seele auch so empfinden.
Und dennoch war bspw. Psalm 88 direkt gefolgt von Psalm 39 ziemlich heftige Kost, sodass bei einigen Morgen- und Abendhoren noch viel umsortiert wurde.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Der Abschlusspsalm der Abendhore ist direkt als letzte Lektüre vor dem Schlafengehen gedacht.
Nicht alle Psalmen bieten sich dafür gleich gut an.
Auch an dieser Stelle waren einige Umverteilungen angebracht.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Als einzige alttestamentliche Schriftlesung kam 1. Mose 2,1-3 an den Samstagabenden hinzu.
Im Judentum beginnt der neue Tag am Abend und der erste Tag der Woche ist für Christen der Sonntag.
Diese Verse aus dem Schöpfungsbericht sollen uns helfen, die neue Woche aus dem Ruhen in unserem Schöpfer zu beginnen.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Nach vielen Wochen kam ich an einer Zusammenstellung an, welche die gesteckten Ziele meiner Ansicht nach gut erfüllt.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="die-liturgie">Die Liturgie&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Keinesfalls ist diese Liturgie als ein sklavisch einzuhaltendes und lebloses Ritual zu verstehen.
Sie soll vielmehr als ein hilfreicher Bezugsrahmen dienen, der uns das Hinwenden zum unsichtbaren Gott, der sich in Jesus sichtbar gemacht hat, erleichtern kann.
Wenn sie dir oder euch dazu nicht dient, ändert sie nach Belieben ab.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Diese Liturgie ist grundsätzlich sehr simpel aufgebaut:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Es gibt &lt;strong>drei Gebetszeiten&lt;/strong>: Morgen, Mittag, Abend
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Gemäß der monastischen Tradition nennen wir sie &lt;em>Laudes&lt;/em> (&amp;ldquo;Lobgesänge&amp;rdquo;), Mittagshore und Abendhore.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>In der Tabelle sind sie bezeichnet mit &amp;ldquo;L&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;M&amp;rdquo; und &amp;ldquo;A&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Jede Gebetszeit (Hore) besteht aus &lt;strong>drei Teilen&lt;/strong>:
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Psalmen (Teil 1)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Lesung aus dem Neuen Testament (Teil NT)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Abschlusspsalm (Teil 2)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Die Bibeltexte sind über &lt;strong>zwei Wochen&lt;/strong> verteilt.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Kleine Besonderheiten:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Psalm 119 besteht aus 22 Strophen und wird nie am Stück gelesen.
Stattdessen sind die einzelnen Strophen über die zwei Wochen verteilt.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Einige Psalmen (53, 70, 108) fehlen, weil sie vollständig in anderen Psalmen enthalten sind (siehe &lt;a class="link" href="#benediktinische-psalmenliturgie" >Benediktinische Psalmenliturgie&lt;/a>).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Die Samstage enthalten nach dem Abschlusspsalm noch einen Abschnitt aus 1. Mose, um die neue Woche aus Gottes Schöpfungsruhe heraus zu beginnen.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Die Psalmen und NT-Texte teilen sich folgendermaßen auf:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>Wochentag&lt;/th>
&lt;th>L 1&lt;/th>
&lt;th>L NT&lt;/th>
&lt;th>L 2&lt;/th>
&lt;th>M 1&lt;/th>
&lt;th>M NT&lt;/th>
&lt;th>M 2&lt;/th>
&lt;th>A 1&lt;/th>
&lt;th>A NT&lt;/th>
&lt;th>A 2&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Sonntag I&lt;/td>
&lt;td>93&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/Joh1,1-18" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Joh1,1-18&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>92&lt;/td>
&lt;td>118&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/Joh17" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Joh17&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>150&lt;/td>
&lt;td>60&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/1Joh2,28ff" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>1Joh2,28&lt;/a>-&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/1Joh3,1-3" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>3,3&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>116&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>3&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>136&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>113&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>30&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>114&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>147&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>115&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Montag I&lt;/td>
&lt;td>29&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/Mt5,17-25" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Mt5,17-25&lt;/a>.&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/Mt7,1-12" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>7,1-12&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>119-I&lt;/td>
&lt;td>25&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/Eph1,15ff" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Eph1,15ff&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>119-II&lt;/td>
&lt;td>32&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/1Joh4,7ff" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>1Joh4,7ff&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>139&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>1&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>120&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>62&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>19&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>121&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>133&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>71&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>122&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Dienstag I&lt;/td>
&lt;td>63&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/Of4" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Of4&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>119-III&lt;/td>
&lt;td>9/10&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/Joh16,19ff" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Joh16,19ff&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>119-IV&lt;/td>
&lt;td>33&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/Joh15,1-17" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Joh15,1-17&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>48&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>101&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>61&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>135&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>28&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>96&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Mittwoch I&lt;/td>
&lt;td>67&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/1Kor1,18ff" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>1Kor1,18ff&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>119-V&lt;/td>
&lt;td>42/43&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/2Kor5,14ff" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>2Kor5,14ff&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>119-VI&lt;/td>
&lt;td>102&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/Mt6,1-18" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Mt6,1-18&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>17&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>6&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>123&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>15&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>107&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>124&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>16&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>7&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>125&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Donnerstag I&lt;/td>
&lt;td>88&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/Phil3,7-14" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Phil3,7-14&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>119-VII&lt;/td>
&lt;td>11&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/Mt6,19ff" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Mt6,19ff&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>119-VIII&lt;/td>
&lt;td>75&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/1Kor13" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>1Kor13&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>145&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>90&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>94&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>140&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>99&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>112&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>26&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Freitag I&lt;/td>
&lt;td>100&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/Phil4,4-13" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Phil4,4-13&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>119-IX&lt;/td>
&lt;td>69&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/Mt16,24-26" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Mt16,24-26&lt;/a>.&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/Mt26,36-46" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>26,36-46&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>119-X&lt;/td>
&lt;td>49&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/Mt11,25ff" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Mt11,25ff&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>46&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>51&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>12&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>31&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>95&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>13&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>41&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Samstag I&lt;/td>
&lt;td>36&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/Tit3,3-7" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Tit3,3-7&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>117&lt;/td>
&lt;td>54&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/R%c3%b6m3,21-26" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Röm3,21-26&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>52&lt;/td>
&lt;td>103&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/Mt18,1-5" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Mt18,1-5&lt;/a>.&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/Mt18,10-14" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>10-14&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>87&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>57&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>58&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>77&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/ELB.HFA/1Mo1,31" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>1Mo1,31&lt;/a>-&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/ELB.HFA/1Mo2,1-3" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>2,3&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>149&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>82&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>86&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>81&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>14&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>85&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Sonntag II&lt;/td>
&lt;td>110&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/Kol1,15ff" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Kol1,15ff&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>47&lt;/td>
&lt;td>45&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/Lk1,46-55" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Lk1,46-55&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>148&lt;/td>
&lt;td>68&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/2Kor2,14-16a" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>2Kor2,14-16a&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>134&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>18&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>72&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>34&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>2&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Montag II&lt;/td>
&lt;td>76&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/R%c3%b6m11,33ff" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Röm11,33&lt;/a>-&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/R%c3%b6m12,1-2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>12,2&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>119-XI&lt;/td>
&lt;td>44&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/Mt5,1-16" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Mt5,1-16&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>119-XII&lt;/td>
&lt;td>79&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/Joh10,1-18" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Joh10,1-18&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>23&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>5&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>126&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>50&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>104&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>127&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>111&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>24&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>128&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Dienstag II&lt;/td>
&lt;td>39&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/Kol3,1-17" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Kol3,1-17&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>119-XIII&lt;/td>
&lt;td>105&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/Eph1,3-8a" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Eph1,3-8a&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>119-XIV&lt;/td>
&lt;td>83&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/2Kor3,18" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>2Kor3,18&lt;/a>.&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/2Kor4,16ff" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>4,16ff&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>4&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>37&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>84&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>40&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Mittwoch II&lt;/td>
&lt;td>143&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/Phil2,5-11" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Phil2,5-11&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>119-XV&lt;/td>
&lt;td>55&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/Hebr12,1-3" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Hebr12,1-3&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>119-XVI&lt;/td>
&lt;td>144&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/R%c3%b6m8,31ff" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Röm8,31ff&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>27&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>64&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>129&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>141&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>146&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>130&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>142&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>8&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>131&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Donnerstag II&lt;/td>
&lt;td>38&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/1Joh1" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>1Joh1,1&lt;/a>-&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/1Joh2,1-6" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>2,6&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>119-XVII&lt;/td>
&lt;td>74&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/Hebr4,12ff" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Hebr4,12ff&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>119-XVIII&lt;/td>
&lt;td>106&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/R%c3%b6m8,1-17" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Röm8,1-17&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>91&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>65&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>73&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>98&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>97&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Freitag II&lt;/td>
&lt;td>78&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/Lk1,67-79" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Lk1,67-79&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>119-XIX&lt;/td>
&lt;td>22&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/Of5" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Of5&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>119-XX&lt;/td>
&lt;td>66&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/Eph3,14ff" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Eph3,14ff&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>138&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>20&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>21&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Samstag II&lt;/td>
&lt;td>59&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/Joh14,15ff" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Joh14,15ff&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>119-XXI&lt;/td>
&lt;td>35&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/Hebr13,9-17" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Hebr13,9-17&lt;/a>.&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/Hebr13,20f" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>20f&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>119-XXII&lt;/td>
&lt;td>137&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9C/Hebr1,1-3" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Hebr1,1-3&lt;/a>.&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NG%C3%9CHebr2,9f" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>2,9f&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>80&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>109&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>132&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>89&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/ELB.HFA/1Mo1,31" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>1Mo1,31&lt;/a>-&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/ELB.HFA/1Mo2,1-3" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>2,3&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>56&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;h2 id="eine-gebrauchsanweisung">Eine Gebrauchsanweisung&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Wie verwende ich diese Liturgie mit Gewinn?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Ich empfehle folgende Schritte als &lt;strong>Vorbereitung&lt;/strong>:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Druck dir die Tabelle aus&lt;/strong>, beispielsweise von &lt;a class="link" href="https://drive.google.com/open?id=14J46EmJiwxjxVElZVYyhl81lPT_moS1P" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>diesem PDF&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Besorg dir gut &lt;strong>lesbare Bibelübersetzungen&lt;/strong>.
Ich empfehle besonders diese Übersetzungen:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Den &lt;strong>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bookfinder.com/isbn/9783878682363/?st=sr&amp;amp;ac=qr&amp;amp;mode=basic&amp;amp;author=&amp;amp;title=&amp;amp;isbn=9783878682363&amp;amp;lang=de&amp;amp;destination=de&amp;amp;currency=EUR&amp;amp;binding=*&amp;amp;keywords=&amp;amp;publisher=&amp;amp;min_year=&amp;amp;max_year=&amp;amp;minprice=&amp;amp;maxprice=" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Münsterschwarzacher Psalter&lt;/a>&lt;/strong> für die Psalmen
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Die neuesten Ausgaben sind manchmal nicht gut erhältlich.
Gebrauchte Ausgaben in älteren Editionen sind oft besser verfügbar und enthalten meist den identischen Text.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Die &lt;strong>Neue Genfer Übersetzung&lt;/strong> (NGÜ) für die NT-Texte&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Eine &lt;em>Elberfelder&lt;/em> oder eine &lt;em>Elberfelder Studienbibel&lt;/em> als genauere Referenz&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Falls es dir hilft:
Setze dir (oder euch, wenn ihr als Gemeinschaft betet) &lt;strong>Zeiten&lt;/strong> für die drei Horen fest.
Ich habe mit verschiedenen Rhythmen experimentiert und fand folgendes hilfreich:
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Laudes 1 und NT nach dem Aufstehen
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Wer bereits eine morgendliche Gebetszeit hat, kann die Texte darin einbauen.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Laudes 2 direkt vor dem Start in den Arbeitstag&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Mittagshore 1 und NT nach dem Mittagessen&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Mittagshore 2 zum Ende der Mittagspause, direkt vor dem Wiedereinstieg in den restlichen Arbeitstag&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Abendhore 1 und NT entweder direkt nach dem Ende des Arbeitstags oder vor dem Abendessen&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Abendhore 2 direkt vor dem Zubettgehen&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Für die &lt;strong>Gebetszeiten selbst&lt;/strong> empfehle ich folgende Herangehensweise:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Bete kurz, bevor du mit dem Lesen beginnst&lt;/strong>.
Danke Gott für den Schatz Seines Wortes und bitte Ihn darum, dass Er diese Texte lebendig macht und direkt zu dir/euch spricht.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Der Apostel Johannes bezeichnet Jesus als &amp;ldquo;das Wort&amp;rdquo; (siehe Johannes 1).
Wenn du die Bibel liest, liest du Jesus und wirst Ihm (über kurz oder lang) begegnen.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Lies die Psalmen und Texte laut&lt;/strong>.
Es macht einen Unterschied, ob du die Texte nur innerlich bewegst oder das Wort Gottes tatsächlich &amp;ldquo;in den Mund nimmst&amp;rdquo; und damit zu einem Teil von dir machst.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Lautes Vorlesen braucht Übung.
Lass dich nicht entmutigen, wenn du anfangs viele Minuten für einen einzigen Psalm brauchst.
Gott freut sich an dem Weg und unsere Fehler überraschen Ihn nicht, noch schmälern sie in geringster Weise Seine unfassbare Liebe zu uns!&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Geh nicht analytisch an den Text heran, sondern &lt;strong>beziehungsorientiert&lt;/strong>.
Wir lesen diese Texte nicht mit dem primären Fokus, um &lt;em>Informationen über Gott&lt;/em> zu gewinnen, sondern um &lt;em>Beziehung zu Gott&lt;/em> zu lernen und zu führen.
Und das tun wir im Fall der Psalmen, indem wir wie Kinder zuerst nachsprechen.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Antworte Ihm nach dem Vorlesen &lt;strong>mit deinen eigenen Worten&lt;/strong>.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Als wir kleine Kinder waren, haben wir nur nachgeplappert, haben viele Fehler gemacht und dabei über weite Strecken ganz mühelos das Sprechen gelernt.
Je mehr wir unsere Muttersprache in uns aufgesogen und praktiziert haben, desto leichter wurde es für uns, auch zunehmend eigene Sätze zu bilden und eigenständig zu sprechen.
Ich bin überzeugt, dass es beim Gebet nicht anders ist.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Antworte Gott an den Stellen innerhalb der Liturgie, wo du in dir eine &lt;strong>Reaktion&lt;/strong> spürst.
Das mag an einer bestimmten Stelle innerhalb eines Psalms sein, nachdem du einen Psalm ganz gelesen hast oder am Ende der Gebetszeit.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Deine Antwort kann in verschiedenstem bestehen, zum Beispiel im wörtlichen Wiederholen eines einzelnen Verses, indem du einen Vers in eigenen Worten ausdrückst, indem du Bedürfnisse, Sehnsüchte, Ängste vor Ihm ausbreitest.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Nachdem du gesprochen hast, heb den Blick und schau Gott in die Augen, als ob er körperlich direkt vor dir oder neben dir wäre.
Wir sind an jedem Ort in Seine liebende und freudige Gegenwart eingehüllt und können ein Gespräch mit Ihm führen wie Abraham (siehe 1. Mose 18).
Wenn du eine Reaktion oder Antwort von Gott wahrnimmst, führe das Gespräch fort.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Lies &lt;strong>so viele&lt;/strong> Texte, wie &lt;strong>für dich gut möglich&lt;/strong> ist.
Jede Person hat ihr grundsätzliches Maß, und jeder von uns hat auch pro Tag und pro Tageszeit unterschiedlich viel Kraft.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Ich empfehle, pro Hore mindestens einen Psalm und den NT-Text zu lesen.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Lass dich nicht entmutigen&lt;/strong>, wenn du einzelne Texte oder eine ganze Gebetszeit aus Müdigkeit auslässt.
In zwei Wochen begegnen dir diese Texte wieder.
Nimm einfach die nächste Gebetszeit kindlich und dankbar aus Gottes Hand entgegen.
Gott freut sich unbändig über jede noch so kleine und noch so unbeholfene Hinwendung!&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Wenn ihr die &lt;strong>Liturgie in Gemeinschaft&lt;/strong> betet, dann können euch womöglich folgende Ergänzungen helfen:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Lest die Psalmen abwechselnd&lt;/strong>.
Dadurch wird es leichter zu einem Gemeinschaftsgebet.
Dafür gibt es verschiedenste Herangehensweisen:
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Teilt euch in &lt;strong>zwei Gruppen&lt;/strong> (A/B), die abwechselnd vorlesen werden.
Oder bestimmt einen Vorbetenden, und bei der Abwechslung betet der Rest der Gemeinschaft - oder die ganze Gemeinschaft antwortet inkl. der/dem Vorbetendem.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Teilt die Texte in &lt;strong>Verspaare&lt;/strong> auf.
Der Münsterschwarzacher Psalter hat bereits Verspaare:
Die Mitte eines Verspaares ist durch ein Sternchen (*) gekennzeichnet.
Entsprechend bieten sich dabei folgende Aufteilungen an:
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Ihr könnt entweder die Verspaare abwechselnd beten (so machen es die Benediktiner):
Gruppe A (oder Vorbetende/r) liest ein Verspaar, Gruppe B (oder alle) lesen das nächste Verspaar&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Oder Gruppe A / Vorbetende/r liest die erste Hälfte eines Verspaares (bis zum Sternchen) und Gruppe B / alle lesen die zweite Hälte des Paares.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sprecht euch vorher ab, wann ihr &lt;strong>Antwortzeiten&lt;/strong> einbauen wollt (siehe Punkt 4 in der vorherigen Liste).
Eine einfache Möglichkeit wäre zum Beispiel, dass nach jedem vollständig gelesenen Psalm und NT-Text Zeit ist, um Gott laut zu antworten.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Lasst den &lt;strong>NT-Text von einer einzelnen Person&lt;/strong> vorlesen.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Ich wünsche Gottes reichen Segen beim Gebrauch Seines Wortes!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Whole Universe Is His Pillow</title><link>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/the-whole-universe-is-his-pillow/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 Oct 2023 20:43:51 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/the-whole-universe-is-his-pillow/</guid><description>&lt;p>In &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Matthew&amp;#43;8%3A18-27&amp;amp;version=NIV" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Matthew 8:18-27&lt;/a> we see Jesus in a crowd.
Because of the multitudes, He decides to go to the other shore and tells His disciples to prepare their boat for departure.
In the midst of this hustle and bustle, a scribe approaches Jesus and expresses his willingness to follow Him wherever He goes.
Jesus does not rebuke the man, but He does tell him what he cannot expect if he really followed Him:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Foxes have dens and birds have nests, but &lt;strong>the Son of Man has no place to lay his head.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>A few moments later, Jesus and His disciples leave the shore.
And just sentences later, we read that the situation had changed dramatically:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Suddenly a furious storm came up on the lake, so that the waves swept over the boat.
&lt;strong>But Jesus was sleeping.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>There are only 4 verses between Jesus saying that He had no place to lay His head and then &lt;em>actually laying His head down&lt;/em> and sleeping completely relaxed in the middle of an extremely dangerous storm.
I believe this teaches us two things:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>First, Jesus has no &lt;strong>place&lt;/strong> to lay His head.
Instead, He has &lt;strong>Someone&lt;/strong> where He can relax, lean back, and sleep peacefully even in the most difficult circumstances.
He knows His Father well enough and has experienced His abundant love and protection to such an extent that He has no trouble falling asleep in the midst of the storm.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Second, Jesus does not have a &lt;strong>single static&lt;/strong> place to lay His head.
Instead, He has &lt;strong>an entire universe&lt;/strong> that fells &amp;ldquo;homey&amp;rdquo; because the &lt;em>Father in the heavens&lt;/em> pervades even the farthest corners of all the galaxies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My prayer is that we would all learn to rest in the love of the Triune God, just as Jesus had learned (and apparently practiced routinely).&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Lieder übersetzen: Warum hören wir einander nicht mehr zu?</title><link>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/lieder-%C3%BCbersetzen-warum-h%C3%B6ren-wir-einander-nicht-mehr-zu/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Mar 2023 10:54:57 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/lieder-%C3%BCbersetzen-warum-h%C3%B6ren-wir-einander-nicht-mehr-zu/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Normalerweise schreibe ich meine Blogbeiträge auf Englisch, aber für dieses Thema bietet es sich deutlich mehr an, auf Deutsch zu schreiben.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Ich möchte über zwei Lieder schreiben, die für mich in ihrer ursprünglichen englischen Fassung geistlich wertvoll sind und bei denen die offizielle deutsche Übersetzung ein paar wenige, aber entscheidende Inhalte völlig entstellt hat.
Und ich möchte darüber schreiben, was das für mich an Mangel in unserer (auch unserer christlichen) Kultur offenbart, einander ernsthaft zuzuhören.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="1-phil-wickham--battle-belongs">1) Phil Wickham — Battle Belongs&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Der &lt;a class="link" href="https://youtu.be/johgSkNj3-A?t=58" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Chorus&lt;/a> fängt so an:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>And when I fight I fight on my knees&lt;br>
With my hands lifted high&lt;br>
Oh God, the &lt;strong>battle&lt;/strong> belongs to You&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Die &lt;a class="link" href="https://youtu.be/WOBvZ5h0cFI?t=62" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>deutsche Übersetzung&lt;/a> klingt so:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Und wenn ich kämpf, dann auf meinen Knien&lt;br>
Heb die Hände zu Dir&lt;br>
Mein Gott, der &lt;strong>Sieg&lt;/strong> gehört Dir allein&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.dict.cc/?s=battle" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Battle&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo; bedeutet &amp;ldquo;Kampf&amp;rdquo; und &lt;strong>nicht&lt;/strong> &amp;ldquo;Sieg&amp;rdquo; — klarer kann ich es nicht ausdrücken.
Der Sieg ist das, was &lt;em>nach&lt;/em> dem Kampf kommt.
Ja, es ist wahr, dass wir Siege in jedem Kampf nur durch Gottes Gnade und Kraft erringen können.
Aber dieses Lied dreht sich ja eben gerade darum, dass ich nicht &lt;strong>erst dann&lt;/strong> Gott die Ehre ausspreche und mein Vertrauen auf ihn setze, wenn der &lt;strong>Kampf vorbei&lt;/strong> ist, sondern &lt;strong>gerade mitten im Kampf&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Ich weiß, dass Übersetzen nicht einfach ist — diesen Blog normalerweise auf Englisch, also nicht in meiner Muttersprache zu schreiben, ist auch nicht immer leicht.
Und bei Liedern muss man auf viele Dinge zusätzlich achten:
Die Silbenanzahlen sollten aufeinander passen, damit keine Lücken oder Zusatznoten entstehen im Vergleich zur Originalmelodie, damit man das Lied leichter mitsingen kann, falls man es auch im Original kennt.
Auch die Betonungen von Wörtern müssen auf den Rhythmus der Melodie passen.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Aber an dieser spezifischen Stelle, die noch dazu die &lt;strong>textlich zentralste Stelle des Liedes&lt;/strong> ist (ansonsten wäre sie nicht der Titel des Liedes), kann ich keinen einzigen Grund erkennen, warum man absichtlich den &lt;em>Inhalt des Liedes abändert&lt;/em>.
Die Silbenanzahl ist identisch, es wäre kein extremer Zungenbrecher, auch mit der Betonung gäbe es keine Probleme.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="2-meredith-andrews--make-room">2) Meredith Andrews — Make Room&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Ein kleineres Beispiel aus der &lt;a class="link" href="https://youtu.be/QxubPpU-iIA?t=145" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Bridge&lt;/a>, das für mich weniger schlimm ist, aber dennoch die gleichen Symptome aufweist:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Shake up the ground of all my tradition&lt;br>
Break down the walls of all my religion&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Your way is better&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Im &lt;a class="link" href="https://youtu.be/TlWcXMdovHg?t=193" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Deutschen&lt;/a> wird daraus:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Reiß Mauern ein, die mich von Dir trennen&lt;br>
Brich alles auf, was Dich in mir eingrenzt&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Dein Plan ist größer&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Ist Sein &lt;em>Weg&lt;/em> wirklich nur das, was Er &lt;em>plant&lt;/em>?
Beinhaltet Sein Weg nicht vielmehr auch &lt;em>Seine Art zu handeln und Seinen Charakter&lt;/em>?
Warum berauben wir den ursprünglichen Text seiner Bandbreite und Tiefe und verengen ihn auf das, was wir meinen verstanden zu haben?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Auch hier sehe ich keinen musikalischen Grund, wegen dem die wörtliche Übersetzung &amp;ldquo;Dein Weg ist besser&amp;rdquo; deutlich schlechter wäre.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="symptome-von-gegenseitiger-ignoranz">Symptome von gegenseitiger Ignoranz&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Wenn wir Lieder aus anderen Sprachen in unsere eigene übersetzen, dann legen wir den Autoren dieser Lieder &lt;em>unsere Worte in den Mund&lt;/em>.
Warum fällt es uns offensichtlich so leicht, einfach über das hinwegzugehen, was die Autoren klar und deutlich in ihren Texten geschrieben haben?
Nehmen wir uns einfach nicht die Zeit den Text genau zu lesen und damit umzugehen?
Wollen wir einfach nur möglichst schnell ein schön klingendes Lied in unser Repertoire aufnehmen und uns (ganz wortwörtlich) &amp;ldquo;aneignen&amp;rdquo; statt zuerst die Worte des Liedes in der Tiefe &lt;em>zu uns selbst&lt;/em> reden zu lassen?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Wenn wir das tun, dann ist klar, dass bei unserem Versuch Anbetungslieder zu übersetzen, letztlich nur eigene Lieder mit anderer Theologie und geklauter Melodie dabei herauskommen!
Ich empöre mich darüber.
Und zwar nicht zuallererst, weil ich sehr genau bin.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Ich glaube, dass wir an vielen Stellen verlernt haben, einander wirklich ernsthaft zuzuhören.
Und dieser Mangel an &amp;ldquo;geöffneten Ohren des Herzens&amp;rdquo; wird niemals nur unsere Kommunikation untereinander als Menschen betreffen, sondern immer auch unsere Bereitschaft, Gott mit offenen Ohren und Herzen zuzuhören.
Ich bin überzeugt, dass es einen &amp;ldquo;besseren Weg&amp;rdquo; gibt.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="wie-kehren-wir-davon-um">Wie kehren wir davon um?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Dieser Weg besteht nicht zuallererst darin, dass wir sklavisch jedes Anbetungslied so wortwörtlich wie nur irgend möglich übersetzen, selbst wenn man es dann nicht mehr singen kann.
Stattdessen liegt meiner Ansicht nach die Lösung darin von Jesus zu lernen.
Wie war er mit Menschen im Gespräch?
Auf welche Weise hat Er ihnen zugehört hat, ihnen geantwortet, ihnen Fragen gestellt?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Wenn wir das lernen, dann lernen wir ganz generell einen anderen Umgang miteinander, einen Umgang, der dem Reich Gottes unter uns entspricht.
Und im natürlichsten Fall befähigt uns das, wie wir uns Jesus zuwenden, Ihm zuhören und von Ihm lernen dazu, auch anderen Gehör zu schenken und ihre Worte ernst zu nehmen.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Lasst mich zwei Beispiele dafür aufzeigen, an denen wir von Ihm, dem Meister, lernen können:&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="a-jesus-im-erbstreit">A) Jesus im Erbstreit&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In Lukas 12,13-15 (NGÜ):&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Einer aus der Menge bat Jesus: »Meister, sag doch meinem Bruder, er soll das väterliche Erbe mit mir teilen!«&lt;br>
Jesus entgegnete ihm: »Lieber Mann, wer hat mich denn zum Richter über euch eingesetzt oder zum Vermittler in euren Erbangelegenheiten?«&lt;br>
Dann wandte er sich an alle und sagte: »Nehmt euch in Acht! Hütet euch vor aller Habgier! Denn das Leben eines Menschen hängt nicht von seinem Wohlstand ab.«&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Jesus hört genau, was der Mann sagt.
Aber Er hört auch &lt;em>mehr als nur das&lt;/em>, was der Mann sagt.
Dass Jesus direkt nach Seiner Antwort an den Mann zur Menge über Habgier spricht, ist nicht einfach ein geschickter rhetorischer Move, sondern Jesus weiß genau, dass sowohl bei dem Mann als auch bei vielen in der Menge (und auch wir sind darunter!) Habgier in den Herzen herrscht.
Deshalb geht Er nicht einfach nur oberflächlich auf das ein, was Ihm der Mann sagt.
Er antwortet vielmehr &lt;em>zutiefst&lt;/em> auf der Ebene, auf welcher der Mann &lt;em>wirklich&lt;/em> eine Antwort braucht, damit nicht länger der Neid sein Leben bestimmt!&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="b-jesus-und-martha">B) Jesus und Martha&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In Lukas 10,40ff (ELB):&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Marta aber war sehr beschäftigt mit vielem Dienen; sie trat aber hinzu und sprach: »Herr, kümmert es dich nicht, dass meine Schwester mich allein gelassen hat zu dienen? Sage ihr doch, dass sie mir helfe!«&lt;br>
Jesus aber antwortete und sprach zu ihr: »Marta, Marta! Du bist besorgt und beunruhigt um viele Dinge; eins aber ist nötig.
Maria aber hat das gute Teil erwählt, das nicht von ihr genommen werden wird.«&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Das Muster ist das gleiche:
Jesus hört die Worte und nimmt darüber hinaus die ganze Person wahr — und Er spricht zur ganzen Person.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Lasst uns Jesus auf die Art und Weise dieser Menschen suchen (also ganz ehrlich und unvollkommen) und lernen, Ihm wirklich zuzuhören und zu gehorchen.
Und wenn wir Ihn selber so erlebt haben und &lt;em>beständig&lt;/em> erleben (wie konnten wir so blind sein zu denken, wir könnten auch nur &lt;em>einen&lt;/em> Handgriff gut tun, ohne uns dabei Seiner kostbaren Gegenwart bewusst zu sein!), dann wird unser Umgang miteinander automatisch ein anderer werden, in dem sowohl die Worte als auch der Mensch dahinter für uns lebendig und nah und wertvoll werden.
Und wenn wir dann sprechen, dann gilt uns die &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/ELB.HFA.NG%C3%9C/Johannes7%2C38" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Zusage von Jesus selbst&lt;/a>:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Wenn jemand an Mich glaubt, werden aus seinem Inneren, wie es in der Schrift heißt, Ströme von lebendigem Wasser fließen.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote></description></item><item><title>Jesus Is My Certificate</title><link>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/jesus-is-my-certificate/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 17:35:37 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/jesus-is-my-certificate/</guid><description>&lt;p>One area I struggle with a lot is the tendency to seek my &lt;em>righteousness&lt;/em> outside of Jesus.
I try to justify my existence or declare myself good by trying to do good or impressive things or by trying to be someone other than I am.
(The Greek word &lt;em>dikaiosyne&lt;/em> in the New Testament is commonly translated with &lt;em>righteousness&lt;/em> and means precisely this: What it is about a person that makes them &amp;ldquo;right&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;good&amp;rdquo;?)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When Jesus entered the scene of human history, He announced the availability of the Kingdom of God to all humans, especially the ones we normally think are completely out of luck in this life (including me).
This means we can step into a different kind of life of eternal quality (He is even so bold as to call it &lt;em>The&lt;/em> Life), and we can do that here and now.
And part of that eternal reality of &amp;ldquo;God always present with us&amp;rdquo; is that we no longer have to try justifying our lives on our own.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Recently, I came upon a wonderful metaphor or analogy for how Jesus justifies us:
&lt;strong>SSL Certificates&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You may remember that many websites run on HTTPS.
(The &amp;ldquo;S&amp;rdquo; in HTTPS stands for SSL (or rather TLS, the more current version of SSL).)
If you check the address bar in your browser, it should show a padlock 🔐 symbol.
That means the communication with a website (e.g. this blog) is secured and the information you send to a website (e.g. to this blog which is hosted on GitHub) is only readable by you and the receiver (and no third party, possibly malicious, in between).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Part of this secure communication are &lt;em>SSL certificates&lt;/em>.
They basically state that a &lt;em>server&lt;/em> hosting a certain website on a &lt;em>domain&lt;/em> (e.g. on the domain &lt;code>jscheytt.github.io&lt;/code>) is really the &lt;em>owner&lt;/em> of that domain.
To establish a certain level of trust, these certificates are &lt;em>signed&lt;/em> by a &lt;em>Certificate Authority&lt;/em> (CA) or multiple CAs.
These are legal entities that basically everybody on the internet has agreed upon to be trustworthy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You can of course easily create a certificate and &lt;em>sign it yourself&lt;/em>.
But if you try to access a website secured by such a self-signed certificate, you are going to see lots of warnings (because browsers don&amp;rsquo;t trust such certificates by default — and you should not either!).
This also applies to our personal &lt;em>dikaiosyne&lt;/em>:
We simply cannot justify ourselves.
We need someone external, someone &lt;em>who is not us&lt;/em> to approve of us and call us good.
Just like the saying goes in &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/ESV.NIV/2%20Corinthians10%3A18" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>2 Corinthians 10&lt;/a>:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>For it is not the one who commends himself who is approved, but the one whom the Lord commends.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Every SSL certificate is only valid for a certain &lt;em>domain&lt;/em> or range of domains.
Short recap:
A domain consists of multiple strings (&amp;ldquo;elements&amp;rdquo;) that are delimited by dots.
The further to the right an element stands, the more importance it has.
The rightmost element is the Top-Level Domain (TLD), e.g. &lt;code>.com&lt;/code>.
Next come the second- and third-level domains.
(Everything below the second level is colloquially called a &amp;ldquo;subdomain&amp;rdquo;.)
If you wanted to secure this website, you could either create a certificate for &lt;code>jscheytt.github.io&lt;/code> or a so-called &lt;em>wildcard certificate&lt;/em> for &lt;code>*.github.io&lt;/code>.
With the latter you could secure all domains running as direct subdomains of &lt;code>github.io&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Now if I try to justify my life on my own (e.g. by relying on my own efforts), I am running my life on &lt;em>my own domain&lt;/em> (e.g. &lt;code>josia-schey.tt&lt;/code>), basically my own kingdom.
I can try as hard as I want to get someone to sign my SSL certificate, and maybe sometimes someone might even approve of me.
But in the end the best I can achieve is an untrustworthy self-signed certificate for my existence.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>However, what Jesus achieved through His life, death on the cross, and resurrection is a &lt;strong>wildcard certificate&lt;/strong> for &lt;code>*.eternal.life&lt;/code>.
He as the Highest Authority in the universe &lt;strong>signed this certificate with His blood&lt;/strong>.
And He invites everybody to &lt;strong>host their lives under His domain&lt;/strong>.
Everybody who places their trust in Him, dies to themselves, and chooses to live in His loving dominion, will have a valid SSL certificate that cannot be corrupted and will never expire.
They just have give up their life (or rather half-life) which they have tried living so far on their own domain (e.g. &lt;code>josia-schey.tt&lt;/code>) and choose to live instead under e.g. &lt;code>josia-scheytt.eternal.life&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There is another neat small catch implied here:
I recently learned that a wildcard certificate is &lt;em>only valid for one level of depth&lt;/em>.
You cannot secure domains with it that sit deeper than the asterisk.
That is, if I have a wildcard certificate for &lt;code>*.eternal.life&lt;/code>, it is only valid for domains like &lt;code>josia-scheytt.eternal.life&lt;/code> but not for any domain like &lt;code>my-personal-kingdom.josia-scheytt.eternal.life&lt;/code> or &lt;code>the-things-from-my-old-life-i-still-try-to-keep.josia-scheytt.eternal.life&lt;/code>.
(To do that I would need another wildcard certificate for &lt;code>*.josia-scheytt.eternal.life&lt;/code>.)
When I submit to Him and let Him live His life through me, there will be no room left for establishing my own kingdom, trying to get things or other people under my control.
God really wanted to have a big family of brothers and sisters all on eye level, and with Him at the center and as the Head — and praise Him for getting it!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Short Notes on the Song of Solomon</title><link>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/short-notes-on-the-song-of-solomon/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2022 11:29:10 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/short-notes-on-the-song-of-solomon/</guid><description>&lt;p>While listening to the Song of Songs recently, the following things stuck with me:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Bridegroom marvels at the beauty of the Bride more than the Bride marvels at the beauty of the Bridegroom.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In chapter 4, the bridegroom praises the beauty of His bride for half the chapter.
At the end of chapter 5, she in turn marvels at His beauty and strength.
In chapter 6, the Bridegroom again speaks of her beauty, sometimes using similar or identical phrases as in chapter 4.
And in chapter 7 the praise from His mouth increases and intensifies, partially even beyond the intimate circle of the two.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For me, this unfolds the following:
Jesus knows our weakness and how much we depend on His affirmation.
His constant and recurring attention is the foundation of our lives.
Telling us the same thing multiple times does not tire Him.
His love for us is unbroken, and He rejoices in every small step we take in devotion to Him.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>And the more steps we take toward Him and with Him, the more we grow in love for Him.
Equally, the more we grow in love for Him, the more He can lavish His love upon us.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But in &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/ELB.HFA/Hoheslied7%2C1" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>chapter 7&lt;/a> we see even more:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>👏 Turn, Sulamith, turn in circles as you dance, for we want to admire you!&lt;br>
😄 What is there to see when I dance the dance of Mahanajim?&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>The beauty of the bride is not just for the Groom.
Those outside the community get to see her beauty as well.
&amp;ldquo;Creation waits in eager expectation for the children of God to be revealed.&amp;rdquo; (&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/ESV.NIV/Romans8%3A19" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Romans 8:19&lt;/a>)
And Jesus delights in this - the beauty of His bride displayed is glory for Him, too!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But this beauty is not made visible to the public by the bride &lt;em>aiming&lt;/em> at it — neither at having the beauty for her own sake nor at being seen.
She asks: &amp;ldquo;What&amp;rsquo;s the matter? I&amp;rsquo;m just dancing for joy as usual!&amp;rdquo;
This is the beauty of life in the Kingdom of God:
We become so rooted in God and in His love for us that real beauty and redeemed joy (even with dancing) grow naturally out of it.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Zechariah — Fasting and Eating for God</title><link>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/zechariah-fasting-and-eating-for-god/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2022 20:28:12 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/zechariah-fasting-and-eating-for-god/</guid><description>&lt;p>I recently heard a sermon about fasting and I was reminded of a dialogue between some Israelites and God in Zechariah 7 and 8:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A group of Israelites have returned from exile in Babylon a little while ago.
During the more than 70 years of exile, they developed a habit of holding fasting days on specific months — a fasting of lament about the destruction of Jerusalem.
They ask if they should continue this practice in light of the ongoing rebuilding of Jerusalem and the temple.
&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/ESV.NIV/Zechariah7%3A5-6" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>The answer God gives&lt;/a> is highly instructive about not just fasting but about our lives as a whole:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>When you fasted and mourned in the fifth month and in the seventh, for these seventy years, &lt;strong>was it for me that you fasted&lt;/strong>?&lt;br>
 And when you eat and when you drink, &lt;strong>do you not eat for yourselves and drink for yourselves&lt;/strong>?&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h2 id="fasting-and-eating-for-whom">Fasting and Eating For Whom?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>There seems to be a way of fasting where you are not fasting for God.
(Let&amp;rsquo;s keep in mind: Fasting is not the mere outward act of abstaining from food, it&amp;rsquo;s abstinence from what normally physically satifies me so I am more receptive for God nourishing me directly.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But not only is there a way of &lt;strong>fasting without God&lt;/strong>, but there is also a way of &lt;strong>eating without God&lt;/strong>.
So you can do &lt;em>everything&lt;/em> in your daily life either with or without God — no matter if one activity seems &amp;ldquo;more holy&amp;rdquo; on the outside than another.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is crucial:
We always have a choice of either doing things &lt;em>for ourselves&lt;/em> — i.e. doing things alone, doing things just the way we want, trusting in our own strength — or &lt;em>for God&lt;/em>.
What is so wonderful about doing things for God is that we are not first and foremost doing something &lt;em>for&lt;/em> Him (although that is certainly part of it) — it&amp;rsquo;s about doing everything &lt;strong>with Him&lt;/strong> and in harmony or symphony with Him.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>That is just another way of stating what the New Testament writers describe as:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>And whatever you do, in word or deed, &lt;strong>do everything in the name of the Lord Jesus&lt;/strong>, giving thanks to God the Father through him.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h2 id="redeeming-our-grief-and-contortions">Redeeming Our Grief and Contortions&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>God could have left it there, saying &amp;ldquo;First learn living in the ways of My goodness, then we can talk about fasting&amp;rdquo; (see the rest of Zechariah 7 after the top verse).
But he does not simply cut off the false practice!
In &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/ESV.NIV/Zechariah8%3A19" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>chapter 8&lt;/a> he revisits the topic and says:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>The fast&lt;/strong> of the fourth, fifth, seventh, and tenth month shall be to the house of Judah &lt;strong>seasons of joy and gladness and cheerful feasts&lt;/strong>.
Therefore love truth and peace!&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>When we return to God, all our sorrow and lament and even all our mislead religious efforts of trying to please Him are redeemed.
He takes it all — all our authentic grief and hurt but also all our perversions of what is good — and turns it into feasts of joy!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Ten Commandments — An Invitation Into Life Itself</title><link>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/the-ten-commandments-an-invitation-into-life-itself/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Sep 2022 18:28:05 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/the-ten-commandments-an-invitation-into-life-itself/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>This is the second part of a series about &lt;a class="link" href="https://jscheytt.github.io/p/the-beauty-of-the-law/" >The Beauty of the Law&lt;/a>.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What is &lt;em>the Law&lt;/em> in the Bible?
In a general sense, the Hebrew word &amp;ldquo;Torah&amp;rdquo; means &amp;ldquo;teaching&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;instruction&amp;rdquo;.
This word often refers to the &lt;em>Pentateuch&lt;/em>, the first five books of the Old Testament.
In a stricter sense, the Law is just the roughly 600 commandments in these five books.
(In Hebrew these are called the &amp;ldquo;Mitzwot&amp;rdquo;.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/ESV.NIRV/Exodus20" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Exodus 20&lt;/a> we read the beginning of these commandments, and it is precisely here that we find the famous &lt;strong>Ten Commandments&lt;/strong>.
The previous part of this series showed how everything in the Law is not only a call to action but also a revelation of God&amp;rsquo;s character.
This part of the series will simply elaborate further on that, this time looking into the Ten Commandments.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Quotation blocks in this article &lt;strong>with quotes&lt;/strong> are from the Bible, quotation blocks &lt;strong>without quotes&lt;/strong> are my interpretation.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h2 id="the-setting">The Setting&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Before we dive into the precise commandments, let&amp;rsquo;s take a few moments to picture the scene:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Israel has lived many hundreds of years in Egypt, first as free people, then at the end as slaves because they thrived too much.
God then calls His servant Moses to liberate His people.
He leads the whole nation out among powerful signs, demonstrating His power and love for Israel.
The biggest of these signs was when God rescued Israel by parting the Red Sea and leading them through it unscathed while their enemies drowned wholesale.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Having rescued these people, He now calls them into the desert.
Moses brings them to Mount Sinai so they can encounter God because He wants to &lt;strong>reveal Himself to every single Israelite personally&lt;/strong> — not just to Moses!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Israelites prepare for three days, purifying themselves.
The encounter at the third day is radical and overwhelming:
The mountain is on fire, dark clouds surround it, a trumpet blows ever louder and louder.
They cannot see the Holy, Invisible God, but they hear His voice, saying:&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="i-am-the-lord-your-god">I Am The Lord Your God&lt;/h2>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;I am the Lord your God.
I brought you out of Egypt. That is the land where you were slaves.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>This is how God addresses His beloved people.
This is what He first says to Israel, the nation with whom He wants to enter into a marriage-like covenant.
He does not start by commanding anything.
His first words answer the questions &amp;ldquo;Who am I?&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Who are you &lt;em>in relation to Me&lt;/em>?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I think this is more important than we often recognize.
We humans are so often confused about who we are.
We need someone outside of ourselves to tell us who we are, to speak identity into our lives so that we can become who we were always meant to be.
We see this &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/ESV.NIRV/Matthew16%3A18" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>with Peter where Jesus tells him&lt;/a> that he is a rock upon whom He will build His church.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>God says that He is &amp;ldquo;the Lord your God&amp;rdquo;.
&amp;ldquo;Lord&amp;rdquo;, in this instance, is the typical rephrasing &amp;ldquo;Adonai&amp;rdquo; instead of the &amp;ldquo;Yahweh&amp;rdquo; name.
And although &amp;ldquo;Yahweh&amp;rdquo; means &amp;ldquo;I am&amp;rdquo;, I want to talk about &lt;strong>lords&lt;/strong> for a moment:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the Old Testament language, being a slave to a master or lord did not only mean &amp;ldquo;working for someone&amp;rdquo;.
It also included &lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;belonging to someone&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>.
If God says that He is the Lord then we are His slaves and we &lt;strong>belong to Him&lt;/strong>.
But I think this extends even further:
Not only do we belong to Him (because He liberated us from the slavery of sin), but &lt;strong>He&lt;/strong> also belongs &lt;strong>to us&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is not what we necessarily see &lt;em>precisely&lt;/em> in this part of scripture, but read the prophets and it&amp;rsquo;s all over the place:
God entered into a marriage covenant with Israel at Mount Sinai.
He tied Himself to this group of people, and in a marriage both spouses &lt;strong>possess each other&lt;/strong>.
They have committed to each other for a lifetime and everything either does will affect the other, both for good and for bad.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Let this sink in:
The Eternal God who made the universe lowers Himself to talk to His creation, those shaky bones and Holy Breath which He formed into humans, and deeply desires to &lt;strong>become one&lt;/strong> with them.
He offers up Himself to these small beings He created in His likeness, telling them &amp;ldquo;You &lt;strong>possess&lt;/strong> Me, and I possess you.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="i-brought-you-out-of-slavery">I Brought You Out Of Slavery&lt;/h3>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>You were not born in freedom.
You were living under the slavery of sin — remember this.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You have not liberated yourself from this slavery on your own.
It was not your politicians (Moses), your money, your connections that saved you from eternal slavery.
It was I who rescued you — so you could become Mine and I could become yours!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Remember Egypt and the signs and miracles with which I lead you out from there.
This is how much you are worth to Me!&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h2 id="you-will-have-no-other-gods-beside-me">You Will Have No Other Gods Beside Me&lt;/h2>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;You shall have no other gods beside Me.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>The Hebrew word for &amp;ldquo;beside Me&amp;rdquo; here means &amp;ldquo;on the same level as Me&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;next to My face&amp;rdquo;.
We hear the same &lt;em>Jealous Husband&lt;/em> here that we also encounter in prophetical books like &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/ESV.NIRV/Hosea2" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Hosea&lt;/a>:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>I want to be the highest priority in your life.
&lt;strong>I am Life&lt;/strong>, and I want to be &lt;em>your life&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>One interesting thing in the whole passage in Exodus 20 is that all the &amp;ldquo;You shall&amp;rdquo; phrases in this chapter can also be translated as &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong>You will&lt;/strong>&amp;rdquo;.
For me this makes the whole section sound not only like &lt;em>commandments&lt;/em> but also like a &lt;strong>promise&lt;/strong> of a different kind of life:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>When you say &amp;ldquo;Yes&amp;rdquo; to Me and enter into this covenant relationship with Me, then this is the kind of life you will lead:
You &lt;em>will&lt;/em> have no other Gods beside Me, you &lt;em>will&lt;/em> not abuse My name, you &lt;em>will&lt;/em> rejoice in the Sabbath, you &lt;em>will&lt;/em> honor your parents, &amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h2 id="you-will-not-make-yourself-idol-images">You Will Not Make Yourself Idol Images&lt;/h2>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;You will not make for yourself a statue or any likeness of anything that is in the sky, on the earth or in the waters.
You will not adore them or serve them.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For I, the Lord your God, am a jealous God, afflicting the guilt of the fathers on the children and grandchildren of those who despise me —
but showing steadfast love to thousands of generations of those who love me and keep my commandments.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>When you enter into this covenant with Me, you will love first of all &lt;strong>Me&lt;/strong> and not the signs of My grace towards you.
You were not made to be the bride or the servant of anybody else but &lt;em>Me&lt;/em> who made you and who has always loved you.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I desire your love!
Your love or disinterest makes a tremendous difference for me.
When you love Me, I will love you back ever more lavishly.
And I will also pour out my kindness and goodness on thousands of generations after you.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you run after others, I will be most jealous and relentless in my pursuit to get back your whole attention.
When you reject me, then I will shake you so you wake up and recognize that all the good in your life which you rely upon comes only from Me.
And you will recognize that &lt;strong>My grace is a thousand times greater&lt;/strong> than the punishment I may enact to bring you back to Me &amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h2 id="you-will-not-exploit-my-name">You Will Not Exploit My Name&lt;/h2>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;You will not pronounce the name of the Lord your God in vain, for the Lord will not hold anyone guiltless who pronounces His name in vain.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Let&amp;rsquo;s look at the words &amp;ldquo;pronounce&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;in vain&amp;rdquo; a bit closer:
The Hebrew verb &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.csv-bibel.de/strongs/h5375" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>&lt;em>nasa&lt;/em>&lt;/a> (for &amp;ldquo;pronounce&amp;rdquo;) mainly means &amp;ldquo;carry&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;lift up&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;take&amp;rdquo;.
I guess that to &lt;em>nasa&lt;/em> God&amp;rsquo;s name means to &amp;ldquo;take His name into our mouths&amp;rdquo; (i.e. pronounce His name out loud) or &amp;ldquo;exalt His name&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Hebrew adjective &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.csv-bibel.de/strongs/h7723" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>&lt;em>shav&lt;/em>&lt;/a> (for &amp;ldquo;vain&amp;rdquo;) is used to describe things that are &amp;ldquo;vain/futile&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;wrong&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;nothing&amp;rdquo;, or even &amp;ldquo;fraud&amp;rdquo;.
On top of that, we know that names in the Jewish culture are not mere words:
They always express the character of that person.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Additionally, we see Jesus making an important point in the &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/ESV.NIRV/Matthew5%3A33-37" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Sermon on the Mount&lt;/a>:
We should never manipulate others by overriding their free will, as we would do e.g. by appealing to God or any high authority so we could make the things we say &lt;em>sound better than what they actually are&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In conjunction, for me this &amp;ldquo;name commandment&amp;rdquo; unfolds like this:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Do not exploit My name and My character to foster your vain projects or — even worse — your fraud!
If you try to simply &lt;em>have your own way&lt;/em> by abusing Me and My love, especially by coercing others to trust your shiny words, you are no longer living from the Tree of Life — and you will reap accordingly.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But when you live in My Kingdom, you can completely afford to openly and vulnerably speak the truth, and you have no need to say anything beyond it.
For I am The Truth, and under My loving reign you will become more and more like Me.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h2 id="keep-the-sabbath">Keep The Sabbath&lt;/h2>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Remember to keep the Sabbath day, to keep it holy.
Six days you shall labor and do all your work, but the seventh day is a day of rest for the Lord your God.
You shall not do any work on it, neither you nor your children, neither your male nor your female servant, not even the animals or the foreigners living in your towns.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For in six days the Lord made the heavens and the earth, the sea and all that is in them, and He rested on the seventh day.
Therefore the Lord blessed the Sabbath day and made it holy.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Among all the commandments in Exodus 20, this is the one that makes it the most obvious that &lt;strong>we should act in certain ways because God does so&lt;/strong> — and not primarily because He &lt;em>says&lt;/em> so.
Children will always learn more deeply by imitating what their parents do.
And we have the greatest and best Father there is and ever will be:
His words and actions will never contradict each other!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>How refreshing and clarifying are the words of the &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/ESV.NIRV/Isaiah58" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>prophet Isaiah about the Sabbath&lt;/a>:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;You will call out to to Me for help and I will answer you.
I will always guide you.
I will satisfy your needs in a land baked by the sun.
You will be like a garden that has plenty of water.
If you keep your foot from the Sabbath, from doing your pleasure on my holy day, and call the Sabbath a delight and the holy day of the Lord honorable, then you will find your joy in Me.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>This is the kind of life we are invited into:
In His Kingdom, we are untied from our reliance upon earthly things and upon our hard work.
By learning to place our trust in Him, we can truly start to enjoy one full day of rest every week because we have learned that &lt;strong>our lives are not in our own hands&lt;/strong>.
There is Someone Infinitely Good providing for us and inviting us into intimacy with Him.
This is truly the place where we find abundant life that is available nowhere else.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="honor-your-parents">Honor Your Parents&lt;/h2>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Honor your father and your mother.
Then you will live a long time in the land the Lord your God is giving you.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>God is a father and He wants to be honored.
On the other hand, God is also a son and wants to honor his father.
We can imitate Him by honoring the people who brought us into this life on a biological level, showing them our deep respect and love — even though our families are often the places where we are wounded the most.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>You have learned to honor Me and obey what I say.
Now, you can subject yourself to your mother and father freely, knowing you are not in their hands but in My loving care first.
In Me, you are finally able to respect them and keep your heart vulnerably open at the same time.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h2 id="you-will-not-kill">You Will Not Kill&lt;/h2>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;You will not murder&amp;rdquo; —
for I am The Life.
You will not take life away from others to secure your own life.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Remember: &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/ESV.NIRV/Galatians2%3A19-21" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Your life ended&lt;/a> when you entered into a covenant with Me, and what you live now, you live in and through Me.
And through Me, &lt;strong>your life will become a place&lt;/strong> where others thrive, &lt;strong>where they come alive&lt;/strong> and their lives start to unfold and blossom.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h2 id="you-will-not-break-marriage">You Will Not Break Marriage&lt;/h2>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;You will not commit adultery&amp;rdquo; —
for I am Faithfulness.
&lt;strong>You will be faithful&lt;/strong> to your spose — not because he or she &lt;em>deserves&lt;/em> it but because you have learned to be faithful to Me, and because you are becoming more and more like Me.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The way you lead your marriage and all your relationships with the other sex &lt;em>will display My relationship with My bride&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h2 id="you-will-not-steal">You Will Not Steal&lt;/h2>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;You will not steal&amp;rdquo; —
for I am your Provider.
I give you more than enough.
You are no longer poor because &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/ESV.NIRV/Romans10%3A12" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>I am rich for all who call on me&lt;/a>.
In this deep bond with Me, you share in this wealth and this fullness of life.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You don&amp;rsquo;t have to live in fear any longer and grasp feverishly for &lt;em>things&lt;/em> to secure your survival.
You are no longer bound to a self-centered and ultimately self-destroying life:
&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/ESV.NIRV/Hebrews10%3A34" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Out of My riches&lt;/a> &lt;strong>you can totally afford to generously give&lt;/strong> to others around you and &lt;strong>love lavishly&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h2 id="you-will-not-lie-against-others">You Will Not Lie Against Others&lt;/h2>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;You will not be a false witness against your neighbor&amp;rdquo; —
for I am The Truth.
You no longer have to fight against others at all.
&lt;strong>You can simply say the truth, and say it in Love&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You can afford to be honest and vulnerable because when you are in Me, nobody can ultimately harm you.
Yes, you can afford to speak the truth even about your enemies, and even if it causes you disadvantage or harm at first — because you are not living from your limited resources but from Me, Life Himself.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h2 id="you-will-not-envy">You Will Not Envy&lt;/h2>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;You will not covet your neighbor&amp;rsquo;s house or wife, male or female servant, ox or donkey or anything that is your neighbor&amp;rsquo;s&amp;rdquo; —
for I am &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/ESV.NIRV/Genesis15%3A1" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>your Great Reward&lt;/a> and the one who satisfies all your deepest needs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Envy for others&amp;rsquo; success, happiness or wealth will not be part of your life because you are not living from a reality of poverty anymore.
No, even better:
You will be free to &lt;strong>genuinely rejoice in the good that others around you experience&lt;/strong>, maybe even more than they themselves enjoy it!&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>&lt;em>This is the second part of a series about &lt;a class="link" href="https://jscheytt.github.io/p/the-beauty-of-the-law/" >The Beauty of the Law&lt;/a>.&lt;/em>
&lt;em>Here is &lt;a class="link" href="https://jscheytt.github.io/p/the-beauty-of-the-law/" >Part 1&lt;/a>.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Beauty of the Law</title><link>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/the-beauty-of-the-law/</link><pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2022 10:32:01 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/the-beauty-of-the-law/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://images.pexels.com/photos/5192347/pexels-photo-5192347.jpeg?cs=srgb&dl=pexels-maor-attias-5192347.jpg&fm=jpg&w=1000" alt="Featured image of post The Beauty of the Law" />&lt;p>&lt;em>This is the first part of a series about The Beauty of the Law.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>About two years ago God began revealing &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/ESV.NIV/Psalm119" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Psalm 119&lt;/a> to me.
This longest of all Psalms with its almost 200 verses is often feared for its length and especially its seemingly bizarre praise of &amp;ldquo;The Law&amp;rdquo;.
This refers to the Torah (the first 5 books of the Bible) and in a stricter sense to the commandments of the Torah.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I was always among those with whom this chapter never rang.
But what I then started realizing is that there is so much personal &lt;strong>closeness&lt;/strong> to God pulsing throughout this Psalm.
The writer is not just &lt;em>talking about&lt;/em> the Law in a general, abstract sense but instead he is constantly addressing God.
This Psalm is a &lt;strong>place of encounter&lt;/strong> with the God of the Law.
And the writer desires to know Him more and endlessly reflects upon the goodness of the whole of Scripture:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The sum of Your Word is truth, and every one of Your righteous rules endures forever!&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>We have come to know that truth is not &lt;em>mere facts&lt;/em> — truth is &lt;strong>Someone&lt;/strong>, a person we can know; you might even say He is &lt;em>The Person&lt;/em>.
Just like the apostle John writes in the prologue of his gospel:
Jesus is the Word In Person.
So when reading Scripture — any part of the Bible, even the Torah and its commandments — you are bound to encounter Him everywhere, all over the place!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Out of this marvelling I suddenly realized that I effectively had no idea what the Law is, even after having read through the whole Bible multiple times in my life.
So I started reading the Torah, exploring it and falling in love with it.
Let me share some beautiful findings from my journey so far:&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="god-reveals-his-character-in-the-law">God Reveals His Character In The Law&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Leviticus in the Old Testament and the gospel of John in the New Testament are &lt;em>the&lt;/em> books of the Bible where the phrase &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.csv-bibel.de/suche/%22ich%20bin%22" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>&amp;ldquo;I am&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a> appears most often (about 50 times in each book).
In John, these are mostly the famous &amp;ldquo;I am&amp;rdquo; sentences by Jesus like &amp;ldquo;I am the Bread of Life,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;I am the Good Shepherd,&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;I am the Resurrection and the Life.&amp;rdquo;
In Leviticus, the most common phrase is &amp;ldquo;(For) I am the Lord (your God).&amp;rdquo;
Although in John the speaker of each &amp;ldquo;I am&amp;rdquo; phrase is not always Jesus, we can get a feeling that the &lt;strong>identity&lt;/strong> of God and His people is front and center in both of these books.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The chapter with the highest density of &amp;ldquo;I am&amp;rdquo; in Leviticus is &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/ESV.NIV/Leviticus19" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>chapter 19&lt;/a>.
This has become one of my favorite chapters in the Bible:
We read all kinds of commandments there, and almost every second or third sentence is &amp;ldquo;(For) I am YHWH (your God)&amp;rdquo;.
It&amp;rsquo;s almost as if these were not mere commands but that they instead reveal something about the very character of God.
Everything in this chapter (and by extension, the whole of the Torah) therefore becomes not just a statement about &lt;strong>what we should do&lt;/strong> but also about &lt;strong>who He is&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="examples-from-leviticus-19">Examples From Leviticus 19&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Let&amp;rsquo;s try a few excerpts from this chapter:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Every one of you shall revere his mother and his father, and you shall keep my Sabbaths: I am the Lord your God.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Not only are we told to honor our parents and lay down our working on the Sabbath, but we also learn that this has something to do with God&amp;rsquo;s nature:
Focussing only on the Sabbath for now, we read in the &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/ESV.NIV/Exodus20%3A11" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Ten Commandments&lt;/a> that &amp;ldquo;in six days the Lord made the heavens and the earth, and He rested on the seventh day.&amp;rdquo;
God wants us to share this resting in Himself, He wants us to rest in that same Peace.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>He gives us commandments not because He is a tyrant who changes His plans at whim but because He is infinitely good and &lt;strong>wants us to share in His character and actions&lt;/strong>.
He made us in His likeness, and Jesus is the one who came to open up God&amp;rsquo;s Kingdom to us so we can truly &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/ESV.NIV/Matthew5%3A45" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>&amp;ldquo;be children of your Father in the Heavens.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here is another &amp;ldquo;law&amp;rdquo; from chapter 19:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>You shall not strip your vineyard bare, you shall leave the fallen grapes for the poor: I am the Lord your God.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>God loves the poor and cares for them.
He will look after them and provision for them, even when people around them ignore them.
Of course we are to act just like Him!
He adopted us in Jesus and we are His sons and daughters, and children learn naturally by imitating their parents.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This way of imitating is something Jesus frequently talks about in the &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/ESV.NIV/John5%3A19" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Gospel of John&lt;/a>:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The Son can do nothing of his own accord, but only what He sees the Father doing.&lt;br>
For wathever the Father does, that the Son does likewise.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Other verses in Leviticus 19 and the Torah in general are harder to discern for me currently.
However, the more you start to explore the Law in search for Him, the more you will find Him.
I don&amp;rsquo;t assume I get everything of the following completely right, but let&amp;rsquo;s take a look at the commandment in verses 6 through 8 about &lt;em>eating the sacrifice meat only during the 3 days&lt;/em> after the act of sacrificing:
At first this sounds illogical and the consequence of exclusion from the sacred community very harsh.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>However, God never meant for us to eat food from sacrificial acts &lt;em>alone&lt;/em>.
He always wanted those who sacrificed an animal for Him to celebrate &lt;strong>together in His presence&lt;/strong>.
By keeping some of this prepared, holy meat and eating it later — at any time of our own liking — we would treat something that was meant for communion and closeness with God and others as something we can exploit selfishly on our own.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>That is not the way He has meant for us to live — neither in the context of sacrifices nor in basically any other part of life.
He wants to make us into beings that can and will naturally live in loving harmony and interaction with Him every moment of each day.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="jesus-is-the-fulfillment-of-the-law">Jesus Is The Fulfillment Of The Law&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The initial followers of Jesus in the first century were Jews.
They knew the Law well, from learning to read and write in the Torah schools and from the synagogue.
It was probably in some sense easier for them than for us today to understand what Jesus meant when He said in Matthew 5:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Do not think that I have come to abolish the Law or the Prophets;&lt;br>
I have not come to abolish them but to &lt;strong>fulfill&lt;/strong> them.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Does that only mean that Jesus simply &lt;em>obeyed&lt;/em> all the commandments in the Torah to the letter?
Is that all there is to Jesus in particular and, more generally, to the life we can lead through Him?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/ESV.NIV/Hebrews1" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>letter to the Hebrews&lt;/a> helps to complete the picture:
It is directed to just such people that came from the Jewish tradition and had gotten to know God the Father through His Son Jesus.
And it draws from the rich imagery of the whole Old Testament to make an important point:
Jesus is the fulfillment of every part of the Old Covenant:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>He is higher than the angels, better than Moses, the 100 % perfect High Priest in the actual, original Sanctuary in the Heavens.
He has offered up Himself as the one ultimate and completely spotless sacrifice.
The Gospel of Matthew, as a complement, makes it clear that Jesus is not only the fulfillment of everything displayed in the &lt;em>Law&lt;/em> but also the fulfillment of everything announced in the &lt;em>Prophets&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So Jesus did not just comply with the Law, He is also The Original that preceded it.
Everything we see in the Old Covenant is ultimately an image, a reduced snapshot of the One True Savior.
It is not the real thing itself, it simply &lt;strong>points towards&lt;/strong> The One To Come and projects a pre-image of Him.&lt;/p>
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;p>The beautiful thing we see in Hebrews is this:
Just because the Old Covenant was a reduced image and an imperfect projection of The Real Thing, we don&amp;rsquo;t have to throw away our Old Testaments because &amp;ldquo;we now have Jesus&amp;rdquo;.
Jesus also said (see above) that He was not going to abolish them, but fulfill them.
Rejecting the Old Testament because it was incomplete would be outright wrong, just as would be rejecting sex in marriage because it is an incomplete image of the union of Christ and His Bride.
Everything on this planet will be an incomplete image of God&amp;rsquo;s glory until He returns.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="how-do-we-now-live-in-this-fulfillment">How Do We Now Live In This Fulfillment?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Romans and Galatians show clearly:
If you try to justify yourself by fulfilling the laws, you have to fulfill them all.
No person has ever managed to do that apart from Jesus.
And He knew perfectly well that our hearts cannot be deeply transformed by merely &amp;ldquo;checking all the boxes&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Discussing which of the Torah commandments are still relevant today and which are not would completely miss the point:
Living in the Kingdom of Jesus is just the opposite of justifying our lives on our own terms and through our own doing.
Instead, Jesus Himself has become our righteousness and the justification for our existence.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>He is inviting us to whole different kind of life:
Not eating from the Tree of Knowing Good and Evil but from Him, the &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/search/ESV.NIV/tree%20of%20life" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Tree of Life&lt;/a>.
By throwing away the ways of our own carefully engineered righteousness and placing our trust in Him, our hearts will be healed and we will no longer need a list of rules to comply with so we can make ourselves good.
Instead, we will live from Him, with Him, in Him.
This is what Jesus describes when He says &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/ESV.NIV/John17%3A3" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>this&lt;/a>:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Now this is eternal life: to know you, the only true God, and to know Jesus Christ, whom You have sent!&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>With this in mind, we can turn towards the Old Testament and especially the Torah &lt;strong>and discover Jesus&lt;/strong> in there and &lt;strong>contemplate the beauty of the Law&lt;/strong> — because it displays His character.
This makes me say with the words of Psalm 119:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Open my eyes and reveal to me the wonders in Your Law!&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>&lt;em>This is the first part of a series about The Beauty of the Law.&lt;/em>
&lt;em>Here is &lt;a class="link" href="https://jscheytt.github.io/p/the-ten-commandments-an-invitation-into-life-itself/" >Part 2&lt;/a>.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Ruth and Boaz are Interlocking With God's Action</title><link>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/ruth-and-boaz-are-interlocking-with-gods-action/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Aug 2022 16:57:34 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/ruth-and-boaz-are-interlocking-with-gods-action/</guid><description>&lt;p>As part of my journey through the &lt;a class="link" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hebrew_Bible" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Tanakh&lt;/a>, I recently came across the book of Ruth.
I want to share some things from this book and its surroundings that really stood out to me afresh.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-surrounding-context-of-scripture">The Surrounding Context of Scripture&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In the Tanakh order of books, Ruth is directly preceded by the book of Proverbs.
The last chapter, Proverbs 31, talks about the &amp;ldquo;woman of noble character&amp;rdquo;.
And in Ruth 3, Boaz interestingly calls Ruth such an &amp;ldquo;woman of noble character&amp;rdquo; (he is using the exact same Hebrew word for &amp;ldquo;noble&amp;rdquo; as in Proverbs 31).
This alone starts showing how it&amp;rsquo;s not about being an Israelite in the first place that gives you God&amp;rsquo;s recognition but &lt;strong>by placing your full trust in Him&lt;/strong>.
We will see in a moment how Ruth is an example of this.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The book directly after Ruth in the Tanakh order is the Song of Songs.
One of the main themes is how the woman and the man seek and chase each other.
Ruth in this story is not chasing any human lover however — she goes after God.
This sets the scene wonderfully to show how even the seemingly most earthly-romantic book in Scripture is not just about humans, it&amp;rsquo;s also about humans together with God:
&lt;strong>We as Jesus&amp;rsquo; bride are to seek Him and chase after Him in all that we do.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="ruth-puts-her-trust-in-god">Ruth Puts Her Trust In God&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>When Ruth and her sister-in-law Orpah rise to accompany their mother-in-law Naomi back to Israel, Naomi tells them to leave for a better future in their homecountry, Moab.
Orpah leaves but &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NIV/Ruth1%3A16-17" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Ruth proclaims her loyalty to Naomi&lt;/a>:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Don&amp;rsquo;t urge me to leave you or to turn back from you.
&lt;strong>Where you go&lt;/strong> I will go, and where you stay I will stay.
&lt;strong>Your people&lt;/strong> will be my people and &lt;strong>your God&lt;/strong> my God.
Where you die I will die, and there I will be buried.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>This alone does not make it look a lot like Ruth would put her trust mostly in God.
But a few verses later, Boaz nails it by speaking out what was deep in Ruth&amp;rsquo;s heart (2:12):&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>May the Lord repay you for what you have done!
May you be richly rewared by the Lord, the God of Israel, &lt;strong>under whose wings you have come to take refuge&lt;/strong>!&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>That&amp;rsquo;s right:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Ruth did not come to &lt;strong>take refuge under Naomi&amp;rsquo;s wings&lt;/strong>:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>This embittered mother-in-law, blinded by her self-centered grief, unable to care for herself as a widow, was in no way a future prospect for Ruth.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Leaning unto this woman when you just lived through a tragic loss yourself was certainly not an easy task and one that &lt;em>you needed to rely on Someone Else&lt;/em>.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ruth would not come to take refuge under the wings of the &lt;strong>people of Israel&lt;/strong> either:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Going to Israel and trying to live there she would certainly face &lt;em>ostracism and poverty&lt;/em> because she was a foreigner, and a widow at that!&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>I suspect that during the 10 years she was married to Mahlon, &lt;em>Ruth got to know the God of Israel intimately&lt;/em> when she experienced the life of a Jewish family through the course of each day, week, and year.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="clinging">Clinging&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We read that Orpah leaves Naomi, but Ruth &amp;ldquo;clings to her&amp;rdquo;.
The Hebrew word for &amp;ldquo;clinging&amp;rdquo; here, &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.csv-bibel.de/strongs/h1692" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>dabaq&lt;/a>, is interesting:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>It&amp;rsquo;s the same word used in Genesis 2 about how a man who will leave his parents and &amp;ldquo;cling to his wife&amp;rdquo; with the two becoming one.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>It&amp;rsquo;s also used for something that &amp;ldquo;sticks&amp;rdquo; to you like glue, just like stains on your hands or your tongue to the roof of your mouth.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>But it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong>not passive&lt;/strong>: The Philistine army &amp;ldquo;sticks to the heels&amp;rdquo; of the Israelites, and Ruth is also told to &amp;ldquo;stick to the maids&amp;rdquo; of Boaz.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>This kind of &amp;ldquo;clinging&amp;rdquo; is the action of attaching yourself to someone and therefore being &lt;strong>very close&lt;/strong> to that person, up to &lt;em>intimacy&lt;/em>, and by being that close, &lt;strong>automatically following them&lt;/strong>.
For me, this is the kind of &amp;ldquo;glueing myself&amp;rdquo; to Jesus that I want to live more every day, just like David says in Psalm 63:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>My soul clings to You; Your right hand upholds me.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>If we not only draw near to Him &lt;em>from time to time&lt;/em> but instead &lt;strong>live&lt;/strong> with Him and stick to His heels, obedience to His words and conformance to His loving character will follow as a natural fruit, just like we read in &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/ESV.NIV/2%20Corinthians3%3A18" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>2 Corinthians 3:18&lt;/a>:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>We all, as we contemplate the Lord&amp;rsquo;s glory with unveiled faces, are being transformed into His image with ever-increasing glory.
This transformation comes from the Lord, who is the Spirit.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h2 id="the-shortsightedness-of-all-the-others">The Shortsightedness Of All The Others&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Elimelech only saw a famine and tried to secure physical survival for his family by moving to Moab — tragically, he and his sons died in spite of his best intentions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Naomi only sees her loss — although she later recognizes and praises God&amp;rsquo;s hand moving in favor of her and Ruth.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The nameless &amp;ldquo;closer redeemer&amp;rdquo; &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/ESV.NIV/Ruth4%3A6" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>only sees his own possession&lt;/a> and tries to secure his family&amp;rsquo;s inheritance and prosperity by relying on his riches.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>But Ruth and Boaz see something far greater.&lt;/strong>
Their eyes are on God first.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Ruth seems to have no problem in trusting God to completely take care of her in a foreign country with (from a human perspective) the outlook of a dim, impoverished existence at the margins of society.
She does not feverishly spring into action nor does she just sit back and do nothing.
Out of her trust in God, she faithfully gathers grain for her mother-in-law and herself throughout every working day, all day long, all the months of the harvest.
And it&amp;rsquo;s only when &lt;em>Naomi&lt;/em> suggests Ruth approach Boaz about the redeemer thing that she does it instead of doing it on her own account.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Boaz does not venture on frantically either:
He understood all along that God was moving here and that he could fully trust Him to bring everything together at the right time.
When Ruth asks him to redeem them, he is not even afraid of the &amp;ldquo;closer redeemer&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>They both see God is at work in everything:
In the famine, in the deaths of Ruth&amp;rsquo;s husband and other family men, in the whole harvest season, in the redemption story — and even beyond what they are going to see with their own eyes!
They see God at work and &lt;strong>willingly intertwine their actions with God&amp;rsquo;s movements&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>And Boaz does not even &amp;ldquo;endanger his family inheritance&amp;rdquo; like the &amp;ldquo;closer redeemer&amp;rdquo; feared.
He gets something far, far better:
A place in the family line of King David and ultimately Jesus, the Son of Man and Son of God.
Now that is a family inheritance!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Job and Truth in the Innermost</title><link>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/job-and-truth-in-the-innermost/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2022 20:27:09 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/job-and-truth-in-the-innermost/</guid><description>&lt;p>About 2 years ago I decided to start reading the Old Testament in the reading order of the &lt;a class="link" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hebrew_Bible" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Tanakh&lt;/a>, the Hebrew bible.
Recently, I came across the book of Job.
This was one among the many books in the Bible I found hard to read or make sense of.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But as part of my journey into &lt;a class="link" href="https://jscheytt.github.io/p/rediscovering-our-hidden-life-in-god/" >rediscovering the abundant yet hidden life in Him&lt;/a> even all the seemingly strange books of the Old Testament start lighting up.
Let&amp;rsquo;s keep in mind that Jesus, the Son of God, was announced by John as &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NIV/John1%3A14" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>&amp;ldquo;the Word&amp;rdquo; Himself&lt;/a>.
What this encompasses for me is that whenever you read the Scriptures — fittingly called &lt;em>God&amp;rsquo;s Word&lt;/em> — you are &lt;strong>reading Jesus&lt;/strong>.
So when we read the Scriptures with the mindset of young Samuel in the temple, saying &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NIV/1%20Samuel3%3A10" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>&amp;ldquo;Speak Lord, Your servant is listening,&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a> and staying on the lookout for Jesus we can surely expect to find Him anywhere in Scripture!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>And thus, the book of Job started lighting up for me as a story about &lt;strong>how to treat one another in suffering&lt;/strong> according to Jesus&amp;rsquo; heart and the prayerful community of love (&lt;a class="link" href="https://jscheytt.github.io/p/rediscovering-our-hidden-life-in-god/" >see Chapter 7 of &amp;ldquo;The Divine Conspiracy&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a>).
It illustrates what a Kingdom way of treating each other in bad times looks like and shows how to truly love a friend who is suffering a great loss.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-the-three-friends-get-right">What The Three Friends Get Right&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>When Job&amp;rsquo;s three friends hear about their friends great misfortune, they set out to find him, &lt;em>not leaving him alone&lt;/em>.
When they find him, they cry out in desperation.
They sit down with him and &lt;em>share his fate&lt;/em> — down in the dust, in the solitude, in the sickness.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We read they even stay with him &lt;em>in silence&lt;/em> and fasting 7 days and nights.
They don&amp;rsquo;t start by saying anything, they start by &lt;em>making themselves one with Job&lt;/em> in his suffering, experiencing and feeling the same pain.
When the conversation starts, they don&amp;rsquo;t start giving wonderful advice on their own.
They &lt;em>let Job begin by sharing his heart&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="where-they-go-wrong">Where They Go Wrong&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>They are &lt;em>not truthful&lt;/em>.
Just like Job, neither of them effectively knows why the trouble and loss came.
But the three friends act as if they knew!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>They try to justify God&amp;rsquo;s actions, &lt;em>speaking on His behalf&lt;/em> motivated by fear.
As if the Great One had any need for small humans hastily jumping to His defense!
Of course God loves it when we honor Him and live out a deep reverence towards Him.
But we cannot force others to do so.
And more importantly, doing anything in our lives &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NIV/Romans14%3A23" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>out of fear instead of trust is effectively sin&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>They say tons of &amp;ldquo;right&amp;rdquo; things — but also out of fear, not out of faith:
Each of them in their own way proclaims God&amp;rsquo;s faithfulness and loyalty towards the ones who stick to Him.
One of them even prophecies that God will reward Job back with double what he lost — and &lt;em>at the end&lt;/em> of the story this is even 100 % fulfilled!
But their &lt;strong>hearts&lt;/strong> are not right:
They just try to stand on the right side of the argument instead of loving their friend by being honest.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The end of the story teaches us that you can say any amount of factually correct things that are legitimately right — but if your heart is not right, God will outright reject it!
&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NIV/Job42%3A7" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>In the final chapter of the book&lt;/a>, He even goes so far as saying:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>I am angry with you and your two friends, because you have not spoken the truth about me, &lt;strong>as my servant Job has&lt;/strong>!&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Ponder this for a moment:
Job&amp;rsquo;s speeches are partially inconsistent, even contradictory about what God does or what God&amp;rsquo;s character is like.
But for God it is Job &lt;strong>in his truthfulness&lt;/strong> who speaks &lt;em>the truth&lt;/em> instead of his friends who emit &lt;em>true facts&lt;/em> &lt;strong>without truthfulness&lt;/strong>, not speaking from a place of vulnerable honesty.
This is what we also clearly see in Psalm 51 where David remarks that God &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/ESV/Psalm51%3A6" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>&amp;ldquo;delights in truth in the inward being&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="its-about-where-god-is-speaking">It&amp;rsquo;s About Where God Is Speaking&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>And then the fourth friend appears: Elihu.
He speaks from a point outside of the spectrum of Job and his friends.
He is not trying to position himself somewhere along the lines of &amp;ldquo;God is always just&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Job has never done any wrong&amp;rdquo;.
Instead He finds the &amp;ldquo;third way&amp;rdquo; beyond their perspective, which is ultimately a perspective of extreme distance to God:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>He approaches Job &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/ESV/Job33%3A6-7" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>in a resolute yet loving manner&lt;/a>.
He talks to both sides about their rights and wrongs.
And he emphasizes the point that this situation (and ultimately, all our lives) is not about who is right or wrong:
It&amp;rsquo;s about &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/ESV.NIV/Job33%3A14" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>God speaking to us&lt;/a> through &lt;strong>all&lt;/strong> of life&amp;rsquo;s circumstances and events.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We see the same pattern in &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NIV/John9" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>John 9&lt;/a> with Jesus and His disciples when they walk past a man who was born blind:
The disciples ask Jesus:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Who has done wrong that this man is suffering so much, his parents or he himself?&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>But then Jesus rightfully asks:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Wait a second — how did the idea enter your minds that this situation is about who sinned when and how?
All this trouble is a way for God to show His glory!&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>And then He goes ahead, heals him and we truly see how &amp;ldquo;the works of God are displayed in him&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We see that Job&amp;rsquo;s loss, the blindness and poverty of the blindborn, and the messes which are our own lifes are all about God constantly speaking to us, wanting to reach His goal of deep connection with us.
&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/NIV/Galatians2%3A19-21" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>My life is not about myself anymore&lt;/a> but about learning to discern where God is working and speaking — and trusting that He is infinitely good.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Rediscovering Our Hidden Life In God</title><link>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/rediscovering-our-hidden-life-in-god/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Aug 2022 18:24:33 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/rediscovering-our-hidden-life-in-god/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://vhx.imgix.net/studygateway/assets/7df85841-6e5b-4ba7-8e58-4563785d7aa6-0fcda344.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Rediscovering Our Hidden Life In God" />&lt;p>How can our lives really change?
How can we actually become good (and not only talk about being good)?
Is deep transformation of our characters on this side of eternity even possible?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I was raised Charismatic/Pentecostal-Christian but the majority of my life often did not exhibit Christlikeness or actual trust in The One.
But in the last 3 years, there were two things that have deeply affected my live and changed my priorities and my heart:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Being in a small group in our church with a shared focus and goal of following Jesus and practicing His presence and His teachings&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Reading the book &amp;ldquo;&lt;a class="link" href="https://dwillard.org/books/divine-conspiracy" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>The Divine Conspiracy&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo; by Dallas Willard (and listening to sermons about topics of the book)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Much has been said about the striking outward similarity of the daily lives of professing Christians and non-Christians — and how we should actually expect to see something very different when we lead a life in accordance with God.
Sadly, none of this has ever helped me to a) identify the many areas in my life where I effectively did not place my reliance upon Jesus and b) learn to put my trust in Jesus.
What this book did for me — more than anything else — was to describe the beauty of God Himself, how well He has crafted this world in which we live, and what an extraordinary kind of life He has meant for us humans: a life in constant connectedness with Him, living out the life He would lead if He would live it here and now.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>From my experience, this book is capable of producing faith in Jesus by displaying Him as the all-competent Master of Life which He really is.
The core of the book (about two thirds) revolve around the Sermon on the Mount, the longest speech and the Master Lecture of Jesus.
These core teachings given by the Son of God never made sense to me in its entirety until I read the interpretations given by Dallas Willard.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One word of caution:
The first 50 to 100 pages are not that easy to read.
On my first try at reading this book I stopped after about 50 pages because it felt too dry and it was not yet becoming clear what point Dallas Willard was trying to drive home.
But if you give him the benefit of the doubt you will get to the gold — that is, to discovering Jesus and the abundant life that He has and is for everyone who puts their complete trust in Him.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One wonderful piece of news is that since a few months &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.fontis-shop.de/products/gott-du-musst-es-selbst-erleben" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>a translation in German has become available&lt;/a>.
That has made it even more accessible for me, even though I read and write a sizable portion of my working day in English!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>An Interpretation of Psalm 45</title><link>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/an-interpretation-of-psalm-45/</link><pubDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2022 18:04:52 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/an-interpretation-of-psalm-45/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.bibleserver.com/ESV.NIV/Psalm45" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Psalm 45&lt;/a> celebrates a royal wedding.
The first part addresses the groom and the second addresses (mostly) the bride.
I am focussing on this second part verses 10 through 17, and I interpret it in one of the ways I see very much fit:
With the groom being both God the Father and God the Son, and the church as His bride.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>ESV/NIV&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Interpretation&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Hear, O daughter, and consider, and incline your ear&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Zone in on me with all your attention, my daughter&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Forget your people and your father’s house&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Leave behind what has given you earthly security by trusting in flesh&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>And the king will desire your beauty&lt;/td>
&lt;td>I look at you with eyes of love; you are so beautiful and I, your Bridegroom, desire you&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Since he is your lord, bow to him&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Surrender yourself to Me completely with your whole life&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>The city of Tyre will come with a gift&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Then you will gain so much more than what you left behind: You are showered with gifts in My proximity and will no longer live in poverty&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>People of wealth will seek your favour&lt;/td>
&lt;td>You are no longer the Deserted Wife but the Desired One&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>All glorious is the princess within her chamber&lt;/td>
&lt;td>To your own joy you discover ever more the beauty with which I made you&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Her gown is interwoven with gold&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Even outsiders marvel at your beauty and praise Me for it&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>In embroidered garments she is led to the king&lt;/td>
&lt;td>I draw you ever closer to Me, your King&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Her virgin companions follow her – those brought to be with her&lt;/td>
&lt;td>You will not stay alone in this: You gain real companions who journey towards the King together with you&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>With joy and gladness they are led along&lt;/td>
&lt;td>In your devotion to Me you experience overflowing joy and rejoicing&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>As they enter the palace of the king&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Your home is with Me&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>In place of your fathers shall be your sons&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Your life is made fertile and provides a space for others to grow&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>You will make them princes in all the earth&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Through the unfolding of My life in yours, your sons and daughters will exercise their responsibility in this world and reign in My Kingdom&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>I will cause your name to be remembered in all generations&lt;/td>
&lt;td>People in all nations will see this&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Therefore nations will praise you forever and ever&lt;/td>
&lt;td>And they will praise the Father, the Son, and the Spirit throughout all eternity&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table></description></item><item><title>The Universe is Very Big</title><link>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/the-universe-is-very-big/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Nov 2021 08:18:44 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/the-universe-is-very-big/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="what-can-we-compare-the-size-of-the-universe-to">What can we compare the size of the universe to?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I was recently starting to wonder about the size of the universe.
It&amp;rsquo;s not like I thought I could really get down to imagining this kind of gargantuan extent.
But I wanted to find a good analogy, so here it goes:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Imagine the distance furthest distance humans will soon travel: the &lt;strong>distance from Earth to Mars&lt;/strong>.
If you are lucky with planning, the shortest route takes almost an entire year (9 months) in a spaceship.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Now let&amp;rsquo;s compare this distance to the &lt;strong>size of the observable universe&lt;/strong>.
The ratio between these two distances is in the order of &lt;strong>$10^{16}$&lt;/strong>.
That means there are 16 orders of magnitude in difference between these two lengths.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What can we compare this to?
Let&amp;rsquo;s scale this down:
We will pretend our planet Earth is the universe.
Now imagine we wanted to drill a hole through the whole planet from one extreme to the other (e.g. from the North Pole to the South Pole).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If we had started drilling the equivalent of the Earth-Mars distance, how far would we have gotten?
One meter?
A millimeter?
The width of a human hair?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It turns out, we would have only gotten as far as the size of &lt;strong>one atom&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="can-we-even-imagine-this-at-all">Can we even imagine this at all?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>For me this only starts to scratch the surface of trying to understand the sheer scale of the universe and the God behind it.
The problem with this analogy?
It still does not help a lot because I believe we humans cannot even really imagine the distance between Earth and Mars yet.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>On Earth we comfortably handle thousands, sometimes maybe tens of thousands of kilometers in our brains.
On our beautiful planet, this is the order of magnitude we are (gladly) confined to.
But the travel from Earth to Mars (i.e. the shortest path) is in the 10s of &lt;strong>millions&lt;/strong> of kilometers.
That is three orders of magnitude above what we normally deal with in daily life!
(If all the fuss around &amp;ldquo;orders of magnitude&amp;rdquo; sounds foreign to you, maybe the well-known video &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0fKBhvDjuy0" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>&amp;ldquo;Powers of Ten&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a> can help you out.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I will just state a hypothesis:
&lt;strong>I believe we humans cannot handle more than 12 orders of magnitude.&lt;/strong>
Everything beyond that will just not fit into our brains.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In everyday life we normally handle about 10 orders of magnitude in space and time.
For space, that is e.g. from 10µm ($10^{-5}$ m) (about the width of a hair) to 10,000 km ($10^{5}$ m) (the &lt;a class="link" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/10,000_km" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>distance between Barcelona and LA&lt;/a>).
For time, that is e.g. from 100 ms (a tenth of a second) to 100 years (about $10^{9}$ s).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If we stretch our imaginations we can go towards tens of thousands of kilometers (now we reach 12 orders of magnitude), and maybe we can begin to imagine 1,000 years and tens of milliseconds.
But I think beyond that we are just lost.
If any object is outside of these ranges we need to scale it up or down and compare it to things within this $10^{12}$ scale.
But if we try to compare things where their ratio is greater than $10^{12}$, our brains are just to tiny to fit these in.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="how-big-is-the-universe-really">How big is the universe really?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Now that we start to find words and numbers to describe the limits of our imagination, I think we start to really become capable of talking about how big the universe really is.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The size of the universe is estimated at multiple tens of billions ($10^{10}$) of lightyears.
One lightyear is roughly $10^{16}$ m, so the size of our universe is in the ballpark of $10^{26}$.
On the other hand, the smallest length that currently fits into our model of the universe is the Planck length at about $10^{-35}$ m.
If we add the absolute values of the exponents, we get the so to speak &amp;ldquo;range of existence&amp;rdquo; of our universe:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>$$
10^{(26+35)} = 10^{61}
$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>That means our universe exists at about &lt;strong>60 orders of magnitude&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As per my above claim, none of us can even begin to imagine this number.
Just try it and keep in mind that 1 order of magnitude means &lt;em>multiply or divide by 10&lt;/em>.
In analogy, 3 orders of magnitude does not mean &lt;em>multiply or divide by 30&lt;/em> but &lt;em>multiply or divide by 1000&lt;/em>.
That means going from 10 orders of magnitude to 15 means &lt;strong>multiplying by 10,000&lt;/strong>.
You can start to see where this is going — but I bet none of us will ever by able to fully grasp such sizes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The above numbers are for space only, but (if I understand that correctly) time is analogous because we are basing it on the same measurements, on the same speed of light (for the upper bound), and the same &lt;a class="link" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Planck_constant" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Planck constant&lt;/a> (for the lower bound).
At the same time, we have to keep in mind that these 60 orders of magnitude come from limited measurements:
We were only able to discover them because of the finite speed of light and the current age of the universe, so it is likely that our universe is &lt;strong>even bigger&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Our human imagination cannot even begin to nibble at these sizes.
I think our perception is even more logarithmic than linear, so we are already pretty well equipped to perceive and compare these orders of magnitude — our range is just ever so narrow.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/e/e7/Observable_universe_logarithmic_illustration.png"
loading="lazy"
alt="An artistic rendition of our universe, drawn at a logarithmic scale with our Sun at the center"
>
&lt;em>An artistic rendition of our universe, drawn at a logarithmic scale with our Sun at the center&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="how-do-we-fit-into-all-this">How do we fit into all this?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I have another number with me, a very simple one:
&lt;strong>5 percent&lt;/strong>.
Or, in other words, 0.05.
(Or $5\cdot10^{-2}$ if you like 😉.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is a rough estimation on &lt;em>the amount of actual matter in the universe&lt;/em>.
When looking at the size and distribution of mass and energy in our universe, then typical baryonic matter makes up less than 5 percent of it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Savor that slowly:
You and me, animals, atoms, the planets, the stars, even all the galaxies, all these account for &lt;strong>not even one twentieth&lt;/strong> of the universe!
And the rest of it is not even empty:
The universe is said to be filled by &lt;a class="link" href="https://science.nasa.gov/astrophysics/focus-areas/what-is-dark-energy" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Dark Energy and Dark Matter&lt;/a>.
(If I could recoin them I would choose the names &lt;em>Invisible Matter&lt;/em> and &lt;em>Invisible Energy&lt;/em>.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Of course this makes one feel very small as a human.
The crazy thing is:
The God who made all this (all matter visible and invisible), the loving Creator of The Heavens and The Earth, the one who is even bigger than 60 orders of magnitude, chose to reduce Himself &lt;em>drastically&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Imagine this:
He created a universe full of wonderful stuff on which most humans will never even lay eyes on (and still they have a right to exist because He rejoices in them!), formed an inhabitable planet with healthy conditions for living, brought all kinds of nature and animals into existence — and then He started making humans &lt;strong>in His own likeness&lt;/strong>.
Hybrid beings, half dust, half Holy Breath, with their own will and therefore a capability to desire and &lt;strong>love Him back&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But He did not stop there:
Because He wanted to subvert all evil in this world with good, He wanted to show us His character and His way of living in the most direct way possible.
So He — became one of us.
The Uncreated and Eternal One laid aside all His privileges and folded up Himself, down to a miniscule body of atoms and molecules to live and breathe on this very planet.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>And not only that:
Although nobobdy even recognized Him (at least in public), He decided to let the verdict for all our betrayal against Him and one another fall upon Himself ✝️.
And in Him the eternal life that He joyfully lives together with His Father, became available to us — to everyone who puts their complete trust in the Son.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>So that is what you look at when you contemplate the universe:
The Perfect Father in all His overflowing beauty and richness and complexity — and at the same time His Son, Jesus, the One who made this loving God visible and touchable for us small humans ❤️.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>