<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Apple on Josia's Blog</title><link>https://jscheytt.github.io/tags/apple/</link><description>Recent content in Apple on Josia's Blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Josia Scheytt</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 25 Sep 2021 17:13:18 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jscheytt.github.io/tags/apple/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Transitioning from Android to iOS — The Good, the Bad, and the Ugly</title><link>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/transitioning-from-android-to-ios-the-good-the-bad-and-the-ugly/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Sep 2021 17:13:18 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://jscheytt.github.io/p/transitioning-from-android-to-ios-the-good-the-bad-and-the-ugly/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This year I have switched from an Android smartphone (Samsung Galaxy J3 (2016)) to an iPhone (SE 2020).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When switching, these things stood out to me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is &lt;strong&gt;no really usable calendar app&lt;/strong&gt;.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was using &lt;a class="link" href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=netgenius.bizcal" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Business Calendar&lt;/a&gt; before and I still miss the month widget.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have settled with &lt;a class="link" href="https://apps.apple.com/de/app/google-kalender-terminplaner/id909319292" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Google Calendar&lt;/a&gt; for now.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;swipe gestures&lt;/strong&gt; from all possible sides of the screen instead of the 1-dimensional top drawer menu are really interesting, and I have grown very fond of them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;emergency contact&lt;/strong&gt; feature is well thought out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Migrating WhatsApp chats&lt;/strong&gt; is only possible via paid 3rd party apps.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I paid 30 USD for &lt;a class="link" href="https://drfone.wondershare.com/buy/drfone-mac-restore-social-app.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Dr. Fone&lt;/a&gt;, connecting both devices to a Desktop/Laptop computer, and it worked flawlessly (missing only the read/unread markers).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;mobile internet usage&lt;/strong&gt; from the stock system is higher than on Android and I have no way reducing it. It used up 17 out of my precious 100 MB monthly quota for system &amp;ldquo;software updates&amp;rdquo; although I deactivated that on the App Store.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Privacy&lt;/strong&gt; is probably a lot better than on Android. See &lt;a class="link" href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2021/03/android-sends-20x-more-data-to-google-than-ios-sends-to-apple-study-says/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt;. Makes sense as Apple is a hardware company and Google is a data company.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have a &lt;strong&gt;lot more space&lt;/strong&gt; on my phone now and I don&amp;rsquo;t have to worry about deleting apps for space.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many of the &lt;strong&gt;default apps&lt;/strong&gt; and settings work really well for me - just I expected also from the MacOS experience.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But I deactivated all Office-ish apps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am &lt;strong&gt;extremely disappointed&lt;/strong&gt; and shocked that there is no solution (not even a paid one) to &lt;strong&gt;activate Do Not Disturb (DND) during calendar events&lt;/strong&gt;.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I used a small Android app called &lt;a class="link" href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=me.camsteffen.polite" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Polite&lt;/a&gt; before and there is no equivalent for it, not even by a long shot!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automatic dark/light mode depending on daytime is very nice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And some iPhone SE-specific things I appreciate:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fingerprint/TouchID was a very good choice. It&amp;rsquo;s kind of sad though that you can add only up to 3 fingerprints (just like on MacOS).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The size is a great relief as it&amp;rsquo;s smaller than most gigantic smartphones from basically all brands nowadays.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The camera is really good even though it&amp;rsquo;s just one lens.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>